虽然世界各国看法不一
MAN ON TV: (FRENCH ACCEN T) Although each of the world's countries
would like to dispute this fact,
但我们法国人坚持认为
we French know the truth:
世上的珍馐美味都来自法国
The best food in the world is made in France.
法国的至尊盛宴都来自巴黎
The best food in France is made in Paris.
而很多人说 巴黎的顶尖美味 都出自Auguste Gusteau大厨之手
And the best food in Paris, some say, is made by Chef Auguste Gusteau.
Gusteau餐厅在巴黎深受欢迎
Gusteau's restaurant is the toast of Paris,
要提前5个月预订
booked five months in advance.
他在法国厨艺界名声大噪
And his dazzling ascent to the top of fine French cuisine
让他的竞争对手嫉妒不已
has made his competitors envious.
他是世上最年轻的5星级厨师
He is the youngest chef ever to achieve a five-star rating.
Gusteau厨师的食谱 "人人能烹饪"
Chef Gusteau's cookbook, Anyone Can Cook!
高居畅销书榜首
climbed to the top of the bestseller list.
不过不是人人都欣赏
But not everyone celebrates its success.
真是滑稽的书名 "人人能烹饪"! (Anton Ego 美食评论家)
Amusing title, Anyone Can Cook!
更滑稽的是 Gusteau对这点深信不疑
What's even more amusing is that Gusteau actually seems to believe it.
我则完全反对 烹饪是很严谨的
I, on the other hand, take cooking seriously.
不可能每个人都会烹饪
And, no, I don't think anyone can do it.
(GUN FIRING )
(THUNDER RUMBLING )
(WOMAN SCREAMING )
(CLATTERING )
这就是我
REMY: This is me.
显然我要重新审视自己的生活
I think it's apparent I need to rethink my life a little bit.
我的问题在哪?
What's my problem?
首先 我是一只老鼠
First of all, I'm a rat.
这意味着生活是艰辛的
Which means life is hard.
其次 我的味觉嗅觉极度发达
And second, I have a highly developed sense of taste and smell.
(SNIFFING )
面粉 鸡蛋 白糖 香荚豆...
Flour, eggs, sugar, vanilla bean...
哦! 柠檬片卷
Oh! Small twist of lemon.
你都能闻出来? 你太有才了
Whoa, you can smell all that? You have a gift.
他是我老哥Emile 很容易记住
REMY: This is Emile, my brother. He's easily impressed.
你能闻出来配料? 这又怎么样?
So you can smell ingredients? So what?
这是我老爸 他没什么特点
This is my dad. He's never impressed.
只不过碰巧是我们部族的首领
He also happens to be the leader of our clan.
有极度发达的嗅觉有什么问题呢?
So, what's wrong with having highly developed senses?
- 哇哦! 别吃这个! - 怎么了?
-Whoa, whoa, whoa! Don't eat that! -What's going on here?
结果证明 那种好闻的气味是老鼠药
Turns out that funny smell was rat poison.
忽然间老爸认为 我的天赋也不是一无是处
Suddenly, Dad didn't think my talent was useless.
我对我的天赋感觉良好
I was feeling pretty good about my gift,
直到老爸给我分配了工作
until Dad gave me a job.
安全
Clean.
- 没错 检查是否有老鼠药 - 完全安全
That's right. Poison checker.
Cleanerific.
绝对安全
Cleanerino.
清净近乎神圣
Close to godliness.
就是安全的意思 清净差不多就是...
Which means clean. You know, cleanliness is close to...
随便吧 下一个
Never mind. Move on.
这让我的爸爸十分自豪
Well, it made my dad proud.
感觉很好吧 Remy? 你协助我们完成了一项神圣的事业
Now, don't you feel better, Remy? You've helped a noble cause.
神圣? 我们是小偷 爸爸
Noble? We're thieves, Dad.
我们偷的都是...垃圾
And what we're stealing is, let's face it, garbage.
如果没人要 那就不叫偷
It isn't stealing if no one wants it.
如果没人要 那我们为什么还要偷?
If no one wants it, why are we stealing it?
(LECTURING )
显然我们俩意见不一致
Let's just say we have different points of view.
在我看来
This much I knew:
宁吃好桃一个 不吃烂桃一筐
If you are what you eat, then I only want to eat the good stuff.
但我爸说...
But to my dad...
食物就是燃料
Food is fuel.
引擎里没有燃料 它就会报废
You get picky about what you put in the tank, your engine is gonna die.
别废话了 吃你的垃圾吧
Now shut up and eat your garbage.
反正也是偷
Look, if we're going to be thieves,
为什么不偷厨房里的好材料呢?
why not steal the good stuff in the kitchen,
而且那些东西都没毒药
where nothing is poisoned?
首先 我们不是小偷
First of all, we are not thieves.
其次 少去厨房 离人远点
Secondly, stay out of the kitchen and away from the humans.
他们很危险
It's dangerous.
我知道 我应该恨人类的
REMY: I know I'm supposed to hate humans,
但他们有自己的独到之处
but there's something about them.
他们不单为了生存 还懂得探索创新
They don't just survive. They discover, they create.
就拿他们的吃的来说
I mean, just look at what they do with food.
我们要如何形容呢?
GUS TEAU ON TV: How can I describe it?
美味食物如同音乐般优美动听 如同图画般赏心悦目
Good food is like music you can taste, color you can smell.
让你被幸福包围
There is excellence all around you.
你只要学会尽情享受
You need only be aware to stop and savor it.
哦 Gusteau说的没错
REMY: Oh, Gusteau was right.
Oh, mmm, yeah.
哦 太好吃了
Oh, amazing.
每种风味都是独一无二的
Each flavor was totally unique.
但如果把两种风味集合到一起
But combine one flavor with another,
就产生了新的体验
and something new was created.
(GASPS )
现在我过着秘密的生活
So now I had a secret life.
(GASPS )
(CACKLING )
只有Emile知道这个秘密
The only one who knew about it was Emile.
嘿 Emile Emile
(WHISPERING FIERCELY) Hey, Emile. Emile.
我找到了一个蘑菇
I found a mushroom.
拜托 你最擅长藏吃的 帮我找个地儿放它吧
Come on, you're good at hiding food. Help me find a good place to put this.
他不理解我 不过跟他一起 我能展现自我
He doesn't understand me, but I can be myself around him.
你为什么这么走?
Why are you walking like that?
我不想总去清洗我的爪子
I don't want to constantly have to wash my paws.
我们用走路的爪子拿东西
Did you ever think about how we walk on the same paws
that we handle food with?
还用来吃东西 你不感觉恶心?
You ever think about what we put into our mouths?
从来没想过
All the time.
吃东西时 我可不想吃我爪子上的味道
When I eat, I don't want to taste everywhere my paws have been.
随你便
Well, go ahead.
不过如果爸爸看见你这么走 他肯定生气
But if Dad sees you walking like that, he's not going to like it.
(SNIFFING )
袋子里是什么?
What have you got there?
啊 哦 哦...
Ah, oh, oh...
(CHUCKLING )
是奶酪?
You found cheese?
还不是一般的奶酪 是山羊奶酪!
And not just any cheese. Tomme de chèvre de pays!
跟我的蘑菇是绝配
That would go beautifully with my mushroom.
而且...
And...
(STUTTERING )
迷迭香! 这个迷迭香
This rosemary! This rosemary
再加上甜草上的露水
with maybe with a few drops from this sweet grass.
都堆到食物那吧 然后我们就能...
Well, throw it on the pile, I guess, and then we'II... You know...
我不能把它跟垃圾混放 这很特别
We don't want to throw this in with the garbage. This is special.
但是我们要在日落之前
But we're supposed to return to the colony
返回鼠群的 你知道爸那个人...
before sundown or, you know, Dad's gonna...
Emile!
他有可能还不知道这里
There are possibilities unexplored here.
我们要烹调一下
We got to cook this.
如何烹调还真是个问题...
Now, exactly how we cook this is the real question...
耶
Yeah.
关键在于不停翻转
The key is to keep turning it.
让烟熏的风味均匀分散
Get the smoky flavor nice and even.
(THUNDER RUMBLING )
要下暴雨了
That storm's getting closer.
嘿 Remy 也许我们不应该这么...
Hey, Remy, you think that maybe we shouldn't be so...
(BOTH SCREAMING )
(MOANING )
(MUNCHING )
你尝尝!
You got to taste this!
吃起来...热辣美味 香酥可口
This is... It's got this kind of... It's burny, melty...
不完全是碳烧风味 绝对是...有点像...
It's not really a smoky taste. It's a certain... It's kind of like a...
(IMITATES EXPLOSION)
就像是"嘣嘣砰"的口味 你感觉呢?
It's got, like, this "ba-boom, zap" kind of taste. Don't you think?
- 你觉得是什么味道? - 闪电味?
-What would you call that flavor? -(HESITANTLY) Lightning-y?
对 闪电味! 我们再来一次
Yeah. It's lightning-y! We got to do that again.
下次风暴来时 我们要上到屋顶上...
Okay, when the next storm comes, we'll go up on the roof...
我知道还缺什么! 藏红花! 来点藏红花就完美了!
I know what this needs! Saffron! A little saffron would make this!
藏红花 我怎么感觉它...
Saffron. Why do I get the feeling
- 在厨房里 - 在厨房里
-it's in the kitchen? -It's in the kitchen.
(SNORING )
(BOTTLES CLINKING )
- 藏红花 - 这可不好
-REMY: Saffron. -Not good.
藏红花
Saffron.
我不喜欢这样 她会醒的
Don't like it. She's gonna wake up.
我来了无数次了
I've been down here a million times.
如果她看烹饪台 就不可能醒来
She turns on the cooking channel, boom, she never wakes up.
你来了无数次了?
You've been here a million times?
藏红花是最合适的配料 Gusteau这么说的
I'm telling you, saffron will be just the thing. Gusteau swears by it.
好吧 谁是Gusteau?
Okay. Who's Gusteau?
他是世上最好的厨师 这本书的作者
Just the greatest chef in the world. Wrote this cookbook.
等等 你看得懂?
(STAMMERING ) Wait. You read?
- 不是全懂 - 哦 伙计 爸知道么?
-Well, not excessively. -Oh, man. Does Dad know?
老爸不知道的事情凑起来可以出一本书
(SCOFFS ) You could fill a book, a lot of books, with things Dad doesn't know.
所以我才要读书 这可是我们的秘密
And they have, which is why I read. Which is also our secret.
我不喜欢秘密
I don't like secrets.
烹饪 阅读 电视
(STUTTERING ) All this cooking and reading and TV-watching
我们还在看书烹饪
while we read and cook.
这是犯罪 你把我卷进来了 我还纵容了你
It's like you're involving me in crime, and I let you.
我为什么要纵容你?
Why do I let you?
那俩孩子干什么去了?
What's taking those kids so long?
天鹰藏红花 产自意大利
Ah, I'Aquila saffron. Italian. Huh?
Gusteau说这是最好的 幸亏这个老女人喜欢烹饪...
Gusteau says it's excellent. Good thing the old lady is a food love...
别以为很神秘 你也可以烹饪
GUS TEAU ON TV: Forget mystique. This is about your cooking.
嘿! 那就是Gusteau Emile 你快看
Hey! That's Gusteau. Emile, look.
胆小鬼做不出好菜
Great cooking is not for the faint of heart.
你一定要充满想象力 充满信心
You must be imaginative, strong hearted.
尝试那些看上去不可能的事
You must try things that may not work.
不要让别人用你的出处身份
And you must not let anyone define your limits
来判断你的能力
because of where you come from.
你唯一的限制就是你的灵魂
Your only limit is your soul.
我说的没错 人人都能烹饪 但只无畏的人才能做到最好
What I say is true. Anyone can cook. But only the fearless can be great.
太有诗意了
Pure poetry.
好景不长
REPORTER: But it was not to last.
由于法国顶尖美食家Anton Ego的批评
Gusteau's restaurant lost one of its five stars
Gusteau的餐馆被降了一个星级
after a scathing review by France's top food critic, Anton Ego.
这对Gusteau是一次严重的打击
It was a severe blow to Gusteau,
伤心欲绝的厨师不久便死去了
and the brokenhearted chef died shortly afterwards,
按常理 这代表着再降一级
which, according to tradition, meant the loss of another star.
Gusteau死了?
Gusteau is dead?
哦!
Oh!
(SQUEAKING )
哦! 哦!
Oh! Oh!
哦!
Oh!
快跑!
Run!
不 你会把她带到鼠群的!
No, you'll lead her to the colony!
(GASPS )
(CLICKING )
- 救命 Remy 救命! - Emile! 摇晃吊灯!
-Help, Remy, help! -Emile! Start swinging the light!
(SQUEAKING )
我争取抓到你
Try to grab you.
(GRUMBLING )
Emile 荡过来
Emile, swing to me.
(GRUNTING )
(CHUCKLING NERVOUSLY)
(EX CLAIMS )
(SIGHS )
(CRACKING )
(CREAKING )
(RATS SQUEAKING )
(SCREAMING )
撤退! 大家撤到船上
Evacuate! Everyone, to the boats.
(ALL CLAMORING )
- 让我过去! - 哦 烹调书
-RAT: Let me through! -The book.
不好意思 借过借过
Excuse me. Move, move.
(AIR HISSING )
(WHIMPERING )
快快快 快走快走
Go, go, go, go. Move, move, move.
把桥放好! 快点快点!
Get the bridge up! Move it, move it!
嘿 Johnny! 快点!
FEMALE RAT: Hey, Johnny! Hurry!
快走 加油
Push off. Come on.
抓紧了!
Get hold!
(GRUNTING )
- 接住孩子! - 把爪子给我
-Take the baby. Here! -Give me your paw.
嘿 等等我!
Hey, wait for me!
(THUNDER CRACKING )
人齐了么? 都在这么?
Is everybody here? Do we have everybody?
- 等等 Remy在哪? - 在这 我来了
-Wait a minute. Where's Remy? -Right here. I'm coming.
我来了!
I'm coming!
坚持住 孩子 给他来个东西抓住
Hold on, Son. Give him something to grab on to.
加油 用这个作船桨 孩子
Come on, boy. Paddle, Son.
加油 抓住
Come on. Reach for it.
你能行的
You can do it.
(GUNSHOT)
- Remy! - 爸爸!
-Remy! -Dad!
加油 你能行的
Come on. You can make it. You can make it.
(GUNSHOT)
(GRUNTS )
伙计们 停下来 等等!
Guys, wait. Stop!
Remy 加油 快划
Remy. Come on. Paddle.
慢点! 等等我 慢点
Hold on! Wait for me. Hold on.
(RATS SCREAMING )
爸爸?
Dad?
走哪边?
Which way?
(WATER ROARING )
(GASPING )
(WATER DRIPPING )
我在等待
REMY: I waited
等待一丝响动
for a sound,
一点声音
a voice,
一个信号
a sign,
什么都行
something.
(STOMACH GROWLING )
(SIGHS )
如果你饿了 到上面去转转 Remy
If you are hungry, go up and look around, Remy.
你为什么闷闷不乐的傻等着?
Why do you wait and mope?
我跟家人朋友走散了
Well, I've just lost my family, all my friends,
也许永远不会再见面了
probably forever.
- 你怎么知道的? - 我...
-How do you know? -Well, I...
你只是一张插图 我为什么跟你说话?
You are an illustration. Why am I talking to you?
因为你失去了亲朋好友 孤身一人
Well, you just lost your family, all your friends. You are Ionely.
是啊 你死了
Yeah. Well, you're dead.
但这和想象力可没关系
Ah, but that is no match for wishful thinking.
如果你留恋身后的路
If you focus on what you've left behind,
就会错失眼前的风景
you'll never be able to see what lies ahead.
到上面去转转吧
Now go up and look around.
(SNIFFING )
(PEOPLE CHATTERING )
哦!
Oh!
(CHUCKLING )
(CORK POPPING )
香槟!
WOMAN: Champagne!
(PEOPLE EX CLAIMING )
你在干什么?
What are you doing?
(SIGHING )
我饿了
I'm hungry.
我也不知道我身处何地
I don't know where I am,
不知道我什么时候才能找到吃的
and I don't know when I'll find food again.
Remy 你应该做的更好 你是厨师
Remy, you are better than that. You are a cook.
厨师自己动手 小偷拿着就走 你不是小偷
A cook makes. A thief takes. You are not a thief.
我饿了
But I am hungry.
(CHUCKLES )
食物会有的 Remy
Food will come, Remy.
食物会呈现在热爱烹饪的人面前
Food always comes to those who love to cook.
(SNIFFING )
- 你认为我跟你闹着玩么? - 你不敢动真格的
-You think I am playing? -You don't have the guts.
(GUNSHOT)
(WOMAN EX CLAIMING )
(BARKING )
巴黎?
Paris?
原来我一直在巴黎的地下?
(CHUCKLING ) All this time I've been underneath Paris?
哇哦
Wow.
太漂亮了
It's beautiful.
这最漂亮
The most beautiful.
Gusteau餐厅? 这是你的饭馆?
Gusteau's? Your restaurant?
你带我来到了你的饭馆
You've led me to your restaurant.
好像是 是的! 我带你来的!
It seems as though I have. Yes. There it is! I have led you to it!
我要去看看
I got to see this.
- 7桌的菜好了 - 马上来
HORST: Ready to go on table seven. COLETTE: Coming around.
- 一份清蒸梭子鱼 - 来了
LALO: One order of steamed pike up. MAN: Coming up.
我需要更多的汤碗
LAROUSSE: I need more soup bowls, please.
- 我要两个烧烤架 - 我需要更多的韭菜
COLETTE: I need two rack of lamb. I need more leeks.
我要两份鲑鱼 三份沙拉 三份鱼片
I need two salmon, three salade composée, and three filet.
沙拉开始制作了
LAROUSSE: Three orders of salade composée working.
在炒干煸鲑鱼
Firing two orders, seared salmon.
三份鱼片开始作了 我需要盘子
Three filet working. I need plates.
HORST: Fire seven. MAN: Three salade composée up.
COLETTE: Don't mess with my mise!
LAROUSSE: Open down low.
MAN: I'm getting buried here.
你好Skinner大厨 晚上好啊
Hello, Chef Skinner. How your night be now?
HORST: Bonjour, chef. LAROUSSE: Hello, Chef Skinner.
晚上好 大厨
-Evening, chef. -WAITER: Ordering deux filet.
嘿 老板 看看谁在这
Hey, boss, look who is here.
Alfredo Linguini Renata的孩子
Alfredo Linguini, Renata's little boy.
- 嗨 - 都长大了 不是么?
-Hi. -All grown up, eh?
你还记得Renata么? Gusteau的旧情人
You remember Renata, Gusteau's old flame?
(CHUCKLING )
- 哦 你多大了... - 他叫Linguini
-Yes. How are you... -Linguini.
对 Linguini 很高兴见到你 你的...
Yes, Linguini. So nice of you to visit. How is...
- 我妈妈? - Renata
-My mother? -Renata.
- 对 Renata 她怎么样了? - 很好
-Yes, Renata. How is she? -Good.
...她享福去了 我是说...
Well, not... She's been better. I mean...
她死了
She died.
哦
Oh.
很抱歉
I'm sorry.
不用 她相信有天堂 现在她就在天堂的庇佑之下
Oh, don't be. She believed in heaven, so she's covered.
在死后 你明白么?
You know, afterlife-wise?
(TITTERS )
- 这是什么? - 她留给你的
-What's this? -She left it for you.
她希望这个能帮我...
I think she hoped it would help me,
在这...找份工作
you know, get a job here.
当然了 Gusteau不会犹豫的
But of course. Gusteau wouldn't hesitate.
你可是Renata的孩子...
Any son of Renata's is more than...
好的 我们留起来备案 如果有合适的工作...
Yes, well, we could file this and if something suitable opens up...
我们已经雇了他了
We have already hired him.
什么? 没有我的批准你就敢决定...
What? How dare you hire someone without my...
我们需要一个收垃圾的人
We needed a garbage boy.
哦 垃圾...
Oh, garbage. Well...
很高兴这事解决了
I'm glad it worked out.
呃...
Uh...
(GULPS )
不敢相信
I can't believe it.
真正的后厨 我要仔细看看
A real gourmet kitchen, and I get to watch.
你看过我的书 让我来考考你
You've read my book. Let us see how much you know, huh?
哪个人是主厨?
Which one is the chef?
哦! 呃...
Oh! Uh...
- 那个人 - 不错
-Oh, that guy. -Very good.
副厨呢?
Who is next in command?
做汤的厨师 那个
The sous chef. There.
当主厨不在的时候他负责
The sous is responsible for the kitchen when the chef's not around.
调味汁厨师 负责调味 很重要
Saucier, in charge of sauces. Very important.
面包房主管 副主管 都很重要
Chef de partie, demi chef de partie, both important.
西厨 负责做菜 很重要
Commis, commis, they're cooks. Very important.
你真是只聪明的老鼠 那个人是干什么的?
You are a clever rat. Now, who is that?
他? 他是小人物
Oh, him? He's nobody.
不是小人物 他也是厨房的一部分
Not nobody. He is part of the kitchen.
他也就算个打杂的
No, he's a plongeur or something.
洗洗盘子 扔垃圾 他不烹饪啊
He washes dishes or takes out the garbage. He doesn't cook.
- 但他可以烹饪 - 哦 不
-But he could. -(SNICKERING ) Uh, no.
你怎么知道的? 我常说什么?
How do you know? What do I always say?
每人都能烹饪
Anyone can cook.
每人都能 不等于每个人都可以
Well, yeah, anyone can. That doesn't mean that anyone should.
这拦不住他 看见没?
(CHUCKLING ) Well, that is not stopping him. See?
他在干什么? 不不 太可怕了!
What is he doing? No. No! No, this is terrible!
(STUTTERING )
他毁了一锅汤 没人发现?
He's ruining the soup. And nobody's noticing?
这是你的餐厅 做点什么
It's your restaurant. Do something.
我能做什么? 我不过是你想象出来的
What can I do? I am a figment of your imagination.
他要毁了那锅汤! 我们要让别人看见...
But he's ruining the soup! We got to tell someone that he's...
(GASPING )
COLETTE: Table five coming up, right now.
(GASPS )
LALO: Coming down the line. COLETTE: Set.
啊!
Ah!
小心烫! 打开烤箱
COLETTE: Hot! Open oven!
(PANTING )
Ah!
就来
HORST: Coming around.
Ooh!
是 主厨 一份小鱼肉 三份羊肉 两份鸭肉
COLETTE: Oui, chef. One filet mignon, three lamb, two duck.
给6号桌烤肉点火
HORST: Fire those soufflés for table six, ja.
- 5分钟 主厨 - 天哪
-COLETTE: Five minutes, chef. -Oh, God.
今晚向您介绍一道肥肝菜
Tonight, I'd like to present the foie gras.
大功告成
It has a wonderful finish.
-REMY: Ooh! -Ah!
Hmm.
(GROANS )
准备给7号桌上菜 快点 我们走
HORST: Ready to go on table seven. Come on! Let's go!
是 主厨!
WAITER: Oui, chef.
(VOMITING )
(SNIFFING )
(GRUNTING INDECISIVELY)
(BUBBLING GENTLY)
Remy! 还等什么?
Remy! What are you waiting for?
你会一直这样冒出来么?
Is this going to become a regular thing with you?
你知道如何补救 这是你的机会
You know how to fix it. This is your chance.
(BELL DINGS )
(GASPS )
汤呢! 汤在哪? 让开
The soup! Where is the soup? Out of my way.
快干活  垃圾工!
Move it, garbage boy!
你在做菜?
You are cooking?
你怎么敢在我的厨房里做菜?
How dare you cook in my kitchen?
你哪来的胆子
Where do you get the gall
甚至企图做这么愚蠢的事情?
to even attempt something so monumentally idiotic?
我应该把你揍一顿然后大卸八块!
I should have you drawn and quartered!
我会的 我认为法律上也会允许我这么做
I'll do it. I think the law is on my side.
(PLEADING )
Larousse  把这个人放进榨鸭里 把他的脑浆挤出来
Larousse, draw and quarter this man
然后暴打一顿再劈了他
after you put him in the duck press to squeeze the fat out of his head.
- 你一直在唧唧歪歪说什么? - 那汤!
-What are you blathering about? -(STUTTERING ) The soup!
汤?
Soup?
别把汤端出去!
Stop that soup!
不!
No!
(PIANO PLAYING SOFTLY)
侍应生
Waiter.
(EX CLAIMS )
Linguini!
你被解雇了!
You're fired!
解-雇!解雇了!
F-l-R-E-D! Fired!
她要见主厨
She wants to see the chef.
但是他...
(STUTTERING ) But he...
(CLEARING THROAT)
- 客人怎么说? - 那不是客人  是个评论家
-What did the customer say? -It was not a customer. It was a critic.
- 是Ego? - 是Solene LeClaire
-Ego? -Solene LeClaire.
- LeClaire? 她说什么了? - 她喜欢那汤
-LeClaire? What did she say? -She likes the soup.
- 等等 - "等等"?  什么意思?
-Wait. -What do you mean, "Wait"?
是你害得我陷入这一团糟
You're the reason I'm in this mess.
有人在谈论你的汤
(SHUSHING ) Someone is asking about your soup.
你到底在玩什么把戏?
What are you playing at?
(STAMMERING )
我依然被解雇么?
Am I still fired?
- 你不能解雇他 - 什么?
-COLETTE: You can't fire him. -What?
LeClaire喜欢这汤  不是吗? 她很确定的告诉了你这点
LeClaire likes it, yeah? She made a point of telling you so.
如果她因此写了一篇评论
If she write a review to that effect
但却发现你把做出这汤的厨师给解雇了...
and find out you fired the cook responsible...
- 他是个垃圾工 - 却做出了她喜欢喝的汤
-(SCOFFS ) He's a garbage boy. -Who made something she liked.
如果我们不支持Gusteau最在乎的信念
How can we claim to represent the name of Gusteau
又如何声称能代表他
if we don't uphold his most cherished belief?
那么那个信念是什么呢? Tatou小姐?
And what belief is that, Mademoiselle Tatou?
每个人都能烹饪
Anyone can cook.
也许我对我们新的垃圾工太严厉了些
Perhaps I have been a bit harsh on our new garbage boy.
他冒了很大的风险
He has taken a bold risk
我们应该奖励这种做法 就好像Gusteau主厨会做的那样
and we should reward that, as Chef Gusteau would have.
如果他想要趟这危险的浑水
If he wishes to swim in dangerous waters,
我们干吗否定他呢?
who are we to deny him?
(CLEARING THROAT)
- 你不是要逃跑么? - 哦  没错
-You were escaping? -Oh, yeah.
既然你表现出了对他厨师事业的浓厚兴趣
Since you have expressed such an interest in his cooking career,
你就应该为此负责
you shall be responsible for it.
(TITTERING )
还有人么?
Anyone else?
那就回去工作
Then back to work.
你要么就是很幸运要么就是很不幸
You are either very lucky or very unlucky.
你要再做一次那汤  并且这一次 我要看着你做
You will make the soup again, and this time, I'll be paying attention.
仔仔细细地看
Very close attention.
他们觉得你可能会成为一个厨师 但你知道我怎么想吗  Linguini?
They think you might be a cook. But you know what I think, Linguini?
我觉得你是一个龌龊的  自大的小...
I think you are a sneaky, overreaching little...
(GASPS )
老鼠!
Rat!
(EX CLAIMING )
- 老鼠! - 抓住它
-Rat! -HORST: Get the rat.
Linguini  拿样东西套住他
Linguini. Get something to trap it.
它在逃 抓住了 抓住了
HORST: It's getting away. Get it, get it, get it.
- 我现在该怎么做? - 杀了它
-What should I do now? -Kill it.
- 现在? - 不 不要在厨房里  你疯了吗?
-Now? -No, not in the kitchen. Are you mad?
你知道如果让人发现我们厨房里有老鼠
Do you know what would happen to us
我们会怎样吗?
if anyone knew we had a rat in our kitchen?
他们会把我们的店关掉
They'd close us down.
我们的声誉现在悬于一线
Our reputation is hanging by a thread as it is.
把它带离这里 远一点 然后杀了它 处理掉它  去吧!
Take it away from here. Far away. Kill it. Dispose of it. Go!
Whoa!
Doh!
(REMY PANTING )
别这么看着我! 你不是唯一一个遇到麻烦的
Don't look at me like that! You aren't the only one who's trapped.
他们希望我再烧一次汤!
They expect me to cook it again!
我的意思是  我没什么野心 我没想要做菜
I mean, I'm not ambitious. I wasn't trying to cook.
我只是努力要远离麻烦
I was just trying to stay out of trouble.
你才能把香料用得出神入化!
You're the one who was getting fancy with the spices!
你把什么扔进去了? 牛至? 不是? 那是什么? 迷迭香?
What did you throw in there? Oregano? No? What? Rosemary?
这是一种香料 是吗? 迷迭香?
That's a spice, isn't it? Rosemary?
你没有把迷迭香扔进汤里面?
You didn't throw rosemary in there?
那么你扔进去的那些都是什么呢...
Then what was all the flipping and all the throwing the...
(SIGHING )
我需要这个工作  我已经失去很多了
I need this job. I've lost so many.
我不知道怎么做菜  而现在我又在 和一个老鼠说话并且以为你...
I don't know how to cook, and now I'm actually talking to a rat as if you...
(GASPS )
你刚刚点头了?
Did you nod?
你一直在点头?
Have you been nodding?
你听得懂我说的话?
You understand me?
所以我没疯!
So I'm not crazy!
等一下  等一下
Wait a second, wait a second.
我不会做菜  是吗?
I can't cook, can I?
但是你...
But you...
你可以 对吗?
You can, right?
好了 别谦虚了 老天 你是只老鼠
Look, don't be so modest. You're a rat, for Pete's sake.
不管你做了什么 他们喜欢
Whatever you did, they liked it.
对  这应该可以
Yeah. This could work.
嘿  他们喜欢那汤!
Hey, they liked the soup!
(SCREAMING )
他们喜欢那汤 你觉得你可以再煮一次吗?
They liked the soup. Do you think you could do it again?
好了  我现在要放你出来了
Okay, I'm going to let you out now.
但我们要一起做这件事  好吗?
But we're together on this. Right?
好的
Okay.
(CHUCKLING )
(SIGHS )
(SOFT PATTERING APPROACHING )
(GRUNTING )
(EX CLAIMING )
就是这里
So this is it.
我的意思是  这不是很大 但这...你知道...
I mean, it's not much, but it's, you know...
不是很大
Not much.
本来还会更糟
It could be worse.
有暖气有电灯有沙发和电视
There's heat and light and a couch with a TV.
所以  我的就是你的
So, you know, what's mine is yours.
你是不是...
Are you...
我是不是在做梦?
Is this a dream?
最美的梦
The best kind of dream.
我们可以分享的梦
One we can share.
(SNORING )
但为什么在这里?
But why here?
为什么是现在?
Why now?
为什么不是这里?
Why not here?
为什么不是现在?
Why not now?
还有比巴黎更好的做梦之地吗?
What better place to dream than in Paris?
早安  小厨师  起床了然后...
Morning, Little Chef. Rise and...
(GASPS )
哦不
Oh, no.
白痴! 我就知道会这样!
Idiot! I knew this would happen!
我让一个老鼠来我家 并且告诉它我的就是它的!
I let a rat into my place and tell him what's mine is his!
鸡蛋  没了!
Eggs, gone!
傻瓜! 它偷了吃的然后上路了! 我还指望什么?
Stupid! He's stolen food and hit the road! What did I expect?
这是我因为信任一只老鼠而得到的...
That's what I get for trusting a...
(STUTTERING )
嗨  那是为我做的吗?
Hi. Is that for me?
Mmm!
好吃  你放了什么进去?
That's good. What did you put in this?
你哪里弄到那个的?
Where'd you get that?
听着  这很好吃  但不能偷东西 我会买些调料的  好吗?
Look, it's delicious. But don't steal. I'll buy some spices, okay?
哦不  我们就要迟到了! 还是上班第一天!
Oh, no. We're going to be late. And on the first day!
快点  小厨师!
(MOUTH FULL) Come on, Little Chef!
"虽然我也像其他评论家那样
"Though I, like many other critic,
"曾批评过Gusteau餐厅 自从主厨去世后就水准下降
"had written off Gusteau as irrelevant since the great chef's death,
"但那份汤却是一次颠覆 让我体会到丰富却又非常微妙的口感"
"the soup was a revelation. A spicy yet subtle taste experience."
- Solene LeClaire写的? - 对!
-Solene LeClaire? -Yes!
"无论如何 Gusteau餐厅已重获我们关注
"Against all odds, Gusteau's has recaptured our attention.
"只有时间能告诉我们 它们是否担得起这样的关注"
"Only time will tell if they deserve it."
(SIGHS )
好了...
Well...
你知道
You know.
我知道这很愚蠢并且奇怪 但我们无法单独做这件事
Look, I know it's stupid and weird, but neither of us can do this alone,
所以我们要一起做  好吗? 你同意吗?
so we got to do it together, right? You with me?
那我们就来做吧!
So let's do this thing!
我...
I...
(GROANING )
(STAMMERING )
(PANTING )
(GASPS )
欢迎来到地狱 现在  重做一次那个汤
Welcome to hell. Now, recreate the soup.
慢慢做  就算要花一整个星期也没关系
Take as much time as you need. All week if you must.
汤
Soup.
(EX CLAIMS )
你这个小...
You little...
(STRIKING )
Ow!
(EX CLAIMS )
(LAUGHING )
(YELPS )
你这该死的...
You son of a...
(SHIVERS )
(EX CLAIMS )
你要...
You got...
(WHIMPERING )
(SCREAMING )
(EX CLAIMS )
(SHRIEKS )
这会坏事的  小厨师!
This is not going to work, Little Chef!
如果再这么下去的话我们会失败的
I'm going to lose it if we do this anymore.
我们要想出点其他的办法
We've got to figure out something else.
其他的办法  不用咬或者掐
Something that doesn't involve any biting, or nipping,
或者在我身上用你的小腿上窜下跳
or running up and down my body with your little rat feet.
咬我! 不行!  跳来跳去! 不行!
The biting! No! Scampering! No!
不能跳或者跑  明白了吗  小厨师?
No scampering or scurrying. Understand, Little Chef?
小厨师?
Little Chef?
噢  你饿了
Oh, you're hungry.
好  让我们来想个办法
Okay. So let's think this out.
你知道如何做菜 我知道如何
You know how to cook, and I know how to appear
装模做样
human.
我们需要制定出一个方案 然后我就能按照你的指令来做
We need to work out a system so that I do what you want
并且看起来我不像被一个小老鼠控制着
in a way that doesn't look like I'm being controlled by a tiny rat chef.
你在听我说吗? 我疯了!  我疯了!
Would you listen to me? I'm insane! I'm insane! I'm insane!
在一个冰箱里和一只老鼠讨论如何在 美食云集的餐厅做菜
In a refrigerator talking to a rat about cooking in a gourmet restaurant.
- 我永远没办法完成! - Linguini?
-I will never pull this off! -Linguini?
我们要交流
We gotta communicate.
我不能一直问一只老鼠是或否...
I can't be constantly checking for a yes or no head shake from a...
老鼠! 我看见了!
The rat! I saw it!
- 老鼠? - 是的  一只老鼠  就在你旁边
-A rat? -Yes, a rat. Right next to you.
你在这里干吗?
What are you doing in here?
我只是让我自己熟悉这些蔬菜什么的
I'm just familiarizing myself with, you know, the vegetables and such.
出去
Get out.
太熟悉蔬菜就会有别的想法 你知道的!
One can get too familiar with vegetables, you know!
好险 你在上面还好吧?
That was close. Are you okay up there?
Whoa!
(GUFFAWING )
你怎么做到的?
How did you do that?
这条件反射可够奇怪的!
That's strangely involuntary!
只看一眼我就知道我们有相同的疯狂想法
REMY: One look and I knew we had the same crazy idea.
好吧
Okay.
嗯?
Huh?
(GROANING )
你带我去哪里? 等等
Where are you taking me? Wait.
(CLATTERING )
Whoa!
等等  对不起
(CHUCKLING ) Wait. I'm sorry.
哇!
Whoa!
好
Okay.
Mmm-hmm...
(SQUEAKS )
(GROANS )
好
Okay.
(GLASS SHATTERING )
(TIRES SCREECHING )
(CRASHING )
(BLABBERING )
Whoa!
祝你健康!
à votre santé!
(GURGLING )
好了
(CHUCKLING ) All right.
这样应该行了
That should do it.
Mmm.
恭喜你 你可以复制出你那碰巧做出来的汤
Congratulations. You were able to repeat your accidental success.
但是小子  如果你要在我厨房生存下去 你就需要知道比做汤更多的东西
But you'll need to know more than soup if you are to survive in my kitchen, boy.
Colette会负责教你如何在这里工作
Colette will be responsible for teaching you how we do things here.
听着  我只是想让你知道
Listen, I just want you to know
我感到很荣幸  为自己能从师于...
how honored I am to be studying under such...
不! 你给我听着 我只是想让你 确确实实知道你在跟谁打交道
No! You listen. I just want you to know exactly who you are dealing with.
在这个厨房里你看到几个女人?
How many women do you see in this kitchen?
嗯  我...
(TITTERING ) Well, I...
- 只有我  你认为这是为什么? - 我想...
-Only me. Why do you think that is? -Well, I...
因为高级餐饮是建立在由愚蠢的老男人
Because haute cuisine is an antiquated hierarchy
所制定的规则上的腐朽阶层
built upon rules written by stupid old men.
这些规则使得女人无法进入这个世界
Rules designed to make it impossible for women to enter this world.
但是我依然在这里  这是怎么回事呢?
But still I'm here. How did this happen?
因为  呃  因为你...
(TITTERING ) Because, well, because you...
因为我是这个厨房里最难搞的厨师
Because I am the toughest cook in this kitchen.
我为了到这里来奋斗了太久太辛苦
I've worked too hard for too long to get here
所以我不会让一个好运的垃圾工 来破坏这一切的
and I am not going to jeopardize it for some garbage boy who got lucky.
明白了吗?
Got it?
(EX CLAIMS )
(LAUGHING )
Wow!
简单易做  方便好吃  Gusteau做中餐
Easy to cook. Easy to eat. Gusteau makes Chinese food
中-易餐
Chine-easy.
(LAUGHING )
- 棒极了 Francois  跟以前一样 - 的确不错  不是吗?
-Excellent work, Fran?ois, as usual. -It's good, isn't it?
我希望你可以为我最近的冷冻食品概念 想出点什么
I want you to work up something for my latest frozen food concept.
Gusteau的玉米小狗
Gusteau's Corn Puppies.
它们很像玉米狗  只是更小一些 一口一个
They're like corn dogs, only smaller. Bite size.
什么是玉米狗?
What are corn dogs?
沾了面糊的劣质香肠放在油里炸 美式食品  你知道的
Cheap sausages dipped in batter and deep fried. You know, American.
想点什么新花样
Whip something up.
也许以Gusteau为主体 再加上Huckleberry Tom的帽子
Maybe Gusteau in overalls and Huckleberry Tom hat.
或者是长了一对大耳朵的狗形玉米
Or as a big ear of corn in doggie make-up.
是的  但是  请高雅点
(HESITANTLY) Yes. But, please, with dignity.
(CLEARING THROAT)
把我律师找来!
Get my lawyer!
遗嘱规定
Well, the will stipulates
如果在去世之日起两年内
that if after a period of two years from the date of death
没有继承人出现
no heir appears,
Gusteau餐厅的营业利润将由他的副厨师长 也就是你  所得
Gusteau's business interests will pass to his sous chef. You.
我知道遗嘱上写了什么
I know what the will stipulates.
我想知道的是这封信是否... 这个小男孩是否会改变这些!
What I want to know is if this letter... If this boy changes anything!
他们看上去不是很像
There's not much resemblance.
一点都不像 他不是Gusteau的儿子
There's no resemblance at all. He is not Gusteau's son.
Gusteau没孩子 那这些时间限制是怎么回事?
Gusteau had no children, and what of the timing of all this?
还有不到一个月就满两年了!
The deadline in the will expires in less than a month!
突然  一个什么小男生 带着他刚去世的妈妈写的信空降过来
Suddenly, some boy arrives with a letter
宣称Gusteau是他爸爸?
from his recently deceased mother claiming Gusteau is his father?
我非常怀疑!
Highly suspect!
- 这是Gusteau的帽子? - 是的 是的
-This is Gusteau's? -Yes, yes, yes.
- 我可以? - 当然
-May I? -Of course.
但是这男孩子不知道
But the boy does not know.
她声称她从没告诉过他 或者Gusteau  并且要求我别告诉他
She claims she never told him, or Gusteau, and asks that I not tell.
- 为什么是你? 她想要什么? - 给孩子一份工作
-Why you? What does she want? -A job for the boy.
- 只是一份工作? - 嗯  是的
-Only a job? -Well, yes.
那么你有什么好担心的 如果他在这里工作
Then what are you worried about? If he works here,
你就可以在我调查的时候看着他
you'll be able to keep an eye on him while I do a little digging.
让我来查查这究竟是不是真的
Find out how much of this is real.
我需要你从那男孩子那里 收集一些DNA样本
I will need you to collect some DNA samples
头发  也许
from the boy. Hair, maybe.
记住我的话  整件事非常可疑
Mark my words. The whole thing is highly suspect.
他知道什么
He knows something.
别紧张  他是一个垃圾工 我觉得你能对付他
Relax, he's a garbage boy. I think you can handle him.
你在干吗?
What are you doing?
我在切蔬菜  切蔬菜?
(STAMMERING ) I'm cutting vegetables. I'm cutting vegetables?
不! 你在浪费精力和时间!
No! You waste energy and time!
你认为做菜是件好玩的事情 就好像妈妈在厨房里做菜?
You think cooking is a cute job, like Mommy in the kitchen?
妈妈永远都不用在用餐高峰时间里
Well, Mommy never had to face
面对汹涌而来的单子
the dinner rush when the orders come flooding in,
每道菜都不同并且都不容易做
and every dish is different and none are simple,
全都需要不同的烹饪时间
and all of the different cooking times,
但却必须同时出现在客人的餐桌上
but must arrive on the customer's table
冒着热气并且很完美!
at exactly the same time, hot and perfect!
每一秒都很宝贵并且你不是妈妈!
Every second counts, and you cannot be Mommy!
这是什么? 保持你的工作台清洁!
What is this? Keep your station clear!
当用餐高峰到来时  会发生什么?
When the meal rush comes, what will happen?
乱七八糟的工作台会拖慢你的效率
Messy stations slow things down.
食物不被拿走  单子堆积起来 那将是灾难
Food doesn't go, orders pile up. Disaster.
我会让你容易记住这点
I'll make this easy to remember.
让你的工作台干净点 否则我会杀了你!
Keep your station clear, or I will kill you!
你的袖子管看上去好像你在上面呕吐过
(EX CLAIMS IN DISGUST) Your sleeves look like you threw up on them.
把你的手和胳膊收起来  紧靠身体 像这样  看见了吗?
Keep your hands and arms in, close to the body. Like this. See?
永远都要回到这个姿势
Always return to this position.
厨师动作都很快  锋利的器具 滚烫的食物  所以把你的胳膊收拢起来
Cooks move fast. Sharp utensils, hot metal, keep your arms in.
这样你才能尽可能少的被割到或者烫到 并且保持你的袖子管清洁
You will minimize cuts and burns and keep your sleeves clean.
厨师的标志: 肮脏的围裙  干净的袖子
Mark of a chef: Messy apron, clean sleeves.
我一直记得Gusteau风格
I know the Gusteau style cold.
在每道菜里 Gusteau大厨总是有意想不到的东西
In every dish, Chef Gusteau always has something unexpected.
我会秀给你看  我记下了他所有的菜谱
I will show you. I memorize all his recipe.
- 永远做一些意想不到的东西 - 不  跟随菜谱做
-Always do something unexpected. -No. Follow the recipe.
- 但你刚刚说... - 不 不
-But you just said that... -No, no, no.
让人出乎意料是他的工作 而我们的工作是要...
It was his job to be unexpected. It is our job to...
- 照着他的菜谱做 - 照着他的菜谱
-Follow his recipes. -Follow the recipe.
你如何在不品尝面包的情况下 分辨它们的好坏?
How do you tell how good bread is without tasting it?
不是靠味道 不是靠外观 而是靠面包皮的声音
Not the smell, not the look, but the sound of the crust.
听
Listen.
(CRUST CRACKING )
噼啪声的交响乐 只有好面包才会发出这种声音
Symphony of crackle. Only great bread sound this way.
做出最好食物的唯一方法就是 在一天开始时第一个挑选食材
The only way to get the best produce is to have first pick of the day
而只有两种方法可以做第一个选材的
and there are only two way to get first pick.
自己种  或者贿赂一个种菜的
Grow it yourself, or bribe a grower.
瞧! 最好的餐厅才能第一个挑菜
Voilà! The best restaurant get first pick.
人们都认为高级餐饮是高高在上的 所以厨师也都是很高高在上的
People think haute cuisine is snooty. So chef must also be snooty.
但并非如此  那边那个Lalo 十二岁的时候离家出走
But not so. Lalo there ran away from home at 1 2.
被马戏团聘请为杂技演员
Got hired by circus people as an acrobat.
然后他被解雇了
(CHUCKLING ) And then he get fired
因为他跟杂技指挥者的女儿搞在一起
for messing around with the ringmaster's daughter.
Horst坐过牢
(CONSPIRATORIAL WHISPER) Horst has done time.
为了什么?
LINGUINl: What for?
没人知道  每次别人问起的时候 他都说不同的版本
No one know for sure. He changes the story every time you ask him.
我欺骗了一家大公司
I defrauded a major corporation.
我用一支圆珠笔抢了法国第二大银行
I robbed the second largest bank in France using only a ballpoint pen.
我在阿维尼翁上方的臭氧层弄了个洞
I created a hole in the ozone over Avignon.
我用这只大拇指杀了个人
I killed a man with this thumb.
永远不要和Pompidou打牌
COLETTE: Don't ever play cards with Pompidou.
他已经被禁止进入拉斯维加斯和蒙特卡洛
He's been banned from Las Vegas and Monte Carlo.
- Larousse为反抗组织走私过军火 - 哪个反抗组织?
-Larousse ran gun for the Resistance. -Which resistance?
他不愿说  显然他们没有取得胜利
He won't say. Apparently, they didn't win.
所以你看
So you see.
我们是艺术家  海盗  然后再是厨师
We are artist, pirate. More than cooks are we.
- 我们? - 是啊  你现在是我们中的一员了  对么?
-We? -Oui. You are one of us now, oui?
是的  还有 谢谢你告诉我关于烹饪的那些忠告
Oui. Thank you, by the way, for all the advice about cooking.
- 也谢谢你 - 为了什么?
-Thank you, too. -For what?
为了接受我的忠告
For taking it.
(MUSIC PLA YIN G ON RADIO )
Huh?
那只老鼠!
The rat!
- 但他是一只... - 我刚刚掉了我的钥匙
-(STUTTERING ) But he is a... -(TITTERING ) I just dropped my keys.
今晚点什么?
Have you decided this evening?
- 你们的汤很好喝  但是... - 但是我们每次都点这个
-Your soup is excellent. But... -But we order it every time.
- 你们还有些什么? - 我们有很好的鹅肝
-What else do you have? -Well, we have a very nice foie gras.
我知道鹅肝
I know about the foie gras.
以前的热门菜  曾经因此而闻名
The old standby, used to be famous for it.
大厨有什么新菜吗?
What does the chef have that's new?
(DOOR SLAMMING )
- 有人问有什么新菜? - 新菜?
-Someone has asked what is new! -New?
对  我该告诉他们什么?
Yes. What do I tell them?
- 那你怎么回答他们的? - 我说我会来问问!
-Well, what did you tell them? -I told them I would ask!
你们在唧唧歪歪什么?
What are you blathering about?
- 客人在问有什么新菜没有 - 我该怎么告诉他们?
-Customers are asking what is new. -What should I tell them?
- 你怎么说的? - 我说我会问问看!
-What did you tell them? -I told them I would ask!
(PONDERING )
这很简单
This is simple.
就拉出一份旧的Gusteau菜谱
Just pull out an old Gusteau recipe,
找出一样我们很久没做过的菜
something we haven't made in a while...
他们知道旧的菜式 他们喜欢Linguini的汤
They know about the old stuff. They like Linguini's soup.
他们要求吃Linguini做出来的菜?
They are asking for food from Linguini?
很多客人喜欢那汤  我们一直这么说
A lot of customers like the soup. That's all we are saying.
我们一直那么说?
Were we saying that?
好极了 如果客人们要尝Linguini做的菜
Very well. If it's Linguini they want
告诉他们Linguini大厨为他们 准备了一份特别的菜肴
tell them Chef Linguini has prepared something special for them.
绝对在菜单上找不到
Something definitely off menu.
哦  别忘了强调
Oh, and don't forget to stress
- 是Linguini派系 - 好的  主厨
-its Linguini-ness. -Oui, chef.
现在给你个机会让你发挥自己的才能 Linguini
Now is your chance to try something worthy of your talent, Linguini.
做一道失传的主厨经典菜 Gusteau羊杂
A forgotten favorite of the chef's, sweetbread à la Gusteau.
- Colette会帮你 - 是 主厨
-Colette will help you. -Oui, chef.
现在  抓紧  我们的客人都饿了
Now, hurry up. Our diners are hungry.
你确定吗? 那份菜谱乱七八糟的
Are you sure? That recipe was a disaster.
Gusteau自己也这么说
Gusteau himself said so.
这正是一个刚刚上手的厨师所需要的
Just the sort of challenge a budding chef needs.
Gusteau羊杂
"Sweetbread à la Gusteau.
"把羊杂放在海藻和粗盐当中
"Sweetbread cooked in a seaweed salt crust
"加上墨鱼爪  蔷薇花瓣
"with cuttlefish tentacle, dog rose purée,
蛤蟆蛋 银耳?
"geoduck egg, dried white fungus?
凤尾鱼甘草酱油
"Anchovy licorice sauce."
我不懂这份食谱 但这是Gusteau 所以...
I don't know this recipe, but it's Gusteau's, so...
Lalo 我们还有泡的小牛肚吗
Lalo! We have some veal stomach soaking, yes?
有 小牛肚
LALO: Yes! The veal stomach, I get that.
小牛肚?
Veal stomach?
噢
Oh!
好
Okay.
(SNIFFING )
我马上就回 在哪...
I'll be right back. Where...
嘿 我要...嘿
Hey, I got to... Hey!
别介意 借用一下 马上就还
Don't mind me. I just need to borrow this real quick.
我看看 在那里
Let's see, over here...
马上就还
I'll be back.
谢谢
Thank you.
抱歉 我要
Excuse me. I'm going to...
显然 我要这个 马上...
Apparently, I need this. I'll be right...
我得要这个
I'm going to pick that up.
我得要点香料
I got some of that spice.
好了
Okay.
你在干什么?
What are you doing? You're supposed
你应该是要准备Gusteau的食谱配料的
to be preparing the Gusteau recipe.
这就是照着食谱做的啊
(STUTTERING ) This is the recipe.
食谱里没说要用白松露油
The recipe doesn't call for white truffle oil!
你还拿了些什么... 你在玩即兴?
What else have you... You are improvising?
没时间让你做实验了 客人都等着在呢
This is no time to experiment. The customer are waiting.
你说的对 我该听你的
You're right. I should listen to you!
- 别打了 - 别什么?
-Stop that! -Stop what?
你疯了 别折腾了 住手
Freaking me out! Whatever you are doing, stop it.
- 特色菜在哪? - 马上就来
-HORST: Where is the special order? -Coming!
- 我以为我们是一起的 - 我们是一起的啊
-I thought we were together on this. -We are together.
- 那你在干嘛 - 很难解释
-Then what are you doing? -It's very hard to explain.
- 特色菜? - 马上
-The special? -Come get it!
等等 我还要加点佐料
Whoa, whoa. I forgot the anchovy licorice sauce.
(EX CLAIMS )
(GASPING )
- 你敢 - 我不敢 不敢 我...
-Don't you dare. -I'm not, I'm not. I'm...
抱歉
Sorry.
Linguini的菜好了吗?
Is Linguini's dish done yet?
一如既往的糟糕 刚刚端出去
Ja. It's as bad as we remember. Just went out.
- 你尝过了吗? - 尝了 在他改配方之前
-Did you taste it? -Ja, of course, before he changed it.
好 什么? 他怎么改了?
Good. What? How could he change it?
他就是改了 注意那门
He changed it as it was going out the door!
啊
Ow!
他们爱死这道菜了
They love it!
其他食客都开始问了 问谁是Linguini
Other diners are already asking about it, about Linguini.
还有七份订单
I have seven more orders!
真是 太好了
That's wonderful.
我也想点一份那样的
I'd like one of those.
特色菜一份
Special order!
那是什么
What is that?
特色菜一份 特色菜一份 特色菜一份
HORST: Special order! Special order! Special order!
敬Linguini
ALL: To Linguini.
- 恭喜 Linguini - 干杯
-Congratulations, Mr. Linguini. -Cheers, ja?
干杯 还有很多呢
LAROUSSE: Drink now, there's plenty.
休息会 小大厨 出来透个气
Take a break, Little Chef. Get some air.
我们真的成功了
We really did it tonight.
Dah!
(GRUNTS )
拿到你的帽子了
(CHUCKLES ) Got your toque!
说真的
Oh, seriously now.
我想和你谈谈 Linguini 在我的办公室
I'd love to have a little talk with you, Linguini, in my office.
- 我有麻烦了吗? - 麻烦?不
-Am I in trouble? -Trouble? No.
喝点小酒 聊点小天 厨师间的闲聊
A little wine, a friendly chat. Just us cooks.
(CHUCKLING GRACIOUSLY)
他再也不需要你的意见了 Colette
The plongeur won't be coming to you for advice anymore, eh, Colette?
他要什么都有了
He's gotten all he needs.
(SNICKERING )
祝贺你的成功 Linguini
Toasting your success, eh, Linguini?
干得好
Good for you.
我只想礼貌一点 其实我不喝酒
I just took it to be polite. I don't really drink, you know.
当然你不喝酒 要是这种烂酒我也不会喝
Of course you don't. I wouldn't either if I was drinking that.
你要是不品品这顶级的红酒 就是真的是个大傻瓜了
But you would have to be an idiot of elephantine proportions
这可是瓶61年的拉图堡
not to appreciate this '61 Chateau Latour.
而你 Linguini 绝对不是个傻瓜
And you, Monsieur Linguini, are no idiot.
让我们为你的成功干杯
Let us toast your non-idiocy.
(SLURPING )
(CLATTERING )
- Remy - Emile?
-Remy! -Emile?
天啊 你还活着
I can't believe it! You're alive!
- 你成功了 - 我以为我再也看不到你了
-You made it! -I thought I'd never see you guys again!
我们都以为你在那急流里活不了
We figured you didn't survive the rapids.
你在吃什么?
And what are you eating?
我也不太清楚
I don't really know.
估计是什么包装袋吧
I think it was some sort of wrapper once.
什么?别 你现在是在巴黎了 我的地盘
What? No. You're in Paris now, baby. My town.
我的兄弟到我的地盘 绝对不能吃人家的剩菜
No brother of mine eats rejectamenta in my town.
(PEOPLE LAUGHING )
(GRUNTING )
Remy 你在偷东西? 你告诉过Linguini 说他可以相信你的
Remy! You are stealing? You told Linguini he could trust you.
- 他可以啊 这是给我兄弟的 - 但那孩子可能会丢了他的工作
-And he can. It's for my brother. -But the boy could lose his job.
他丢了我还不是一样也丢了 一切都在我的掌握下 好吗?
Which means I would, too. It's under control, okay?
- 再来点? - 不行了 不过 好吧
-More wine? -I shouldn't, but... Okay.
你的手艺是在哪里训练的 Linguini
So, where did you train, Linguini?
训练?
Train? All right.
你该不会让我以为你这是第一次做菜吧?
Surely you don't expect me to believe this is your first time cooking?
- 不是 - 我就知道
-It's not. -I knew it!
这是我的第一 二 三 四 第五次做菜
It's my... Second, third, fourth... Fifth time.
星期一才是我第一次做的菜
Monday was my first time.
不过我以前倒是经常扫垃圾
But I've taken out the garbage lots of times before that...
好 好 再来点酒
Yes, yes. Have some more wine.
告诉我 Linguini 你有什么爱好
Tell me, Linguini, about your interests.
你喜欢动物吗?
Do you like animals?
什么?动物?什么动物?
(CHUCKLING ) What? Animals? What kind?
一般的 小猫 小马 豚鼠
The usual, dogs, cats, horses, guinea pigs,
老鼠
rats.
我给你拿了点
I brought you something to...
(SCREAMS )
别 别 别 别
No, no, no, no!
吐出来 马上
Spit that out right now!
我得教教你什么才是食物 闭上眼睛
I have got to teach you about food. Close your eyes.
现在轻轻的咬... 不 不 不
Now take a bite of... No! No! No!
- 别就这么吞下去了啊 - 太晚了
-Don't just hork it down! -Too late.
给你
Here.
慢点嚼 细细品尝味道
Chew it slowly. Only think about the taste.
- 感觉到没? - 还没
-See? -Not really.
乳脂 咸咸的 甜甜的 很硬的橡子
Creamy, salty sweet, an oaky nuttiness.
- 尝出来了吗 - 橡子倒是吃出来了
-You detect that? -Oh, I'm detecting nuttiness.
闭上眼睛 尝尝这个
Close your eyes. Now taste this.
天壤之别 对不对? 又香又脆 回味无穷
Whole different thing, right? Sweet, crisp, slight tang on the finish.
- 好 - 现在两个一起吃
-Okay. -Now, try them together.
好
Okay.
我想我尝出点什么来了
I think I'm getting a little something there.
- 可能是坚果 - 对吧?
-It might be the nuttiness. -See?
- 也许是味道 - 就是那种感觉
-Could be the tang. -That's it.
现在 想象一下 把世界上 每一种伟大的味道
Now, imagine every great taste in the world
用无限的组合来调配
being combined into infinite combinations.
那是前无古人的美味 大发明就此诞生
Tastes that no one has tried yet! Discoveries to be made!
我想...
I think...
- 你又把我绕昏了 - 算了
-You lost me again. -(GROANING ) Yeah.
不过那还挺有意思的
But that was interesting.
是我吃过的最好的垃圾... 嘿 我们在干什么
Most interesting garbage I ever... Hey! What are we doing?
老爸还不知道你还或者
Dad doesn't know you're alive yet!
我们得回族里去 每个人都会高兴死的
We've got to go to the colony! Everyone will be thrilled!
- 嗯 但是 - 什么
-Yeah! But... -What?
我现在 有点事...
Thing is, I kind of have to...
有什么事比家庭还重要?
What do you "have to" more than family?
这里还有什么是更重要的?
What's more important here?
这个...
Well, I...
来玩玩也无伤大雅
It wouldn't hurt to visit.
- 你有没有宠物鼠 - 没有
-Have you had a pet rat? -No.
- 你有没有拿老鼠做实验 - 没有
-Did you work in a lab with rats? -No.
你和老鼠住一起?
Perhaps you lived in squalor at some point?
没有 没有 没有
Nopety nopety no.
你知道一些老鼠的事 你知道 你知道!
You know something about rats! You know you do!
天知道 地知道 啦啦啦 小呀么小老鼠哈
You know who know do whacka-doo. Ratta-tatta.
- 为什么这么叫 - 什么?
-Hey! Why do they call it that? -What?
Ratatouille 这是道炖菜吧 为什么这么叫
Ratatouille. It's like a stew, right? Why do they call it that?
如果你要命名食物
If you're going to name a food,
应该选个听起来就美味的名字
you should give it a name that sounds delicious.
Ratatouille听起来就不好吃啊 听起来像"老鼠"和"屁屁"
Ratatouille doesn't sound delicious. It sounds like "rat" and "patootie."
老鼠 屁屁听起来一点都不好吃
Rat patootie. Which does not sound delicious.
可惜了 酒都喝光了
Regrettably we are all out of wine.
我的儿子回来了
My son has returned!
(ALL CHEERING )
找人代替你做毒药检测器简直是不可能
And finding someone to replace you for poison checker has been a disaster.
没什么被下毒了 谢天谢地 不过这可不简单啊
Nothing's been poisoned, thank God, but it hasn't been easy.
- 你把这事弄的复杂了 - 我知道 对不起 爸爸
-You didn't make it easy. -I know. I am sorry, Dad.
没事 重要的是你回家了
Well, the important thing is that you're home.
嗯 呃 关于这件事
(STUTTERING ) Yeah, well, about that...
你消瘦了好多 怎么回事
You look thin. Why is that?
没吃饱还是为了显示与众不同?
A shortage of food, or a surplus of snobbery?
一个人在外面闯荡不容易吧
It's tough out there in the big world all alone, isn't it?
嗯 但我不是小孩了
Sure, but it's not like I'm a kid anymore.
- 嘿 嘿 怎么了 - 我自己 能照顾好自己
-Hey. Hey, boy. What's up? -I can take care of myself.
我在不远处找了个好房子 我会常回家看看的
I've found a nice spot not far away, so I'll be able to visit often.
没什么能比现实的残酷更能...
Nothing like a cold splash of reality to make you...
- 回家看看? - 嗯 我保证 常回来
-Visit? -I will. I promise. Often.
- 你不打算留在家里? - 不 这不是什么大不了的 爸 我就是
-You're not staying? -No. It's not a big deal, Dad. I just...
你不会以为我会一辈子都呆在家里吧
You didn't think I was going to stay forever, did you?
小鸟总归是要离巢高飞的
Eventually, a bird's got to leave the nest.
我们不是鸟 我们是老鼠
We're not birds. We're rats.
我们从不离巢穴 我们只会越来越壮大
We don't leave our nests. We make them bigger.
- 也许我是与众不同的老鼠 - 也许你根本就不是老鼠
-Well, maybe I'm a different kind of rat. -Maybe you're not a rat at all.
说不定这还是件好事
Maybe that's a good thing.
嘿 今晚的乐队真不错
Hey! The band's really on tonight, huh?
老鼠 只知道索取 老爸
Rats. All we do is take, Dad.
我已经厌倦了 我想做点什么出来
I'm tired of taking. I want to make things.
我想给这世界做点什么
I want to add something to this world.
- 你说话的口气像个人类 - 他们不像你说的那么坏
-You're talking like a human. -Who are not as bad as you say.
- 是吗?你凭什么这么肯定 - 噢 老天
-Oh, yeah? What makes you so sure? -Oh, man.
我 有机会
(HESITANTLY) I've been able to observe them
近距离 观察他们
at a close-ish sort of range.
- 有多近 - 反正够近了
-Yeah? How close? -Close enough.
而且他们 也没有你说的那么坏
And they're, you know, not so bad as you say they are.
跟我来 我给你看点东西
Come with me. I got something I want you to see.
我就不跟你们去了
You know, I'm going to stay here.
锁门前把地板和灶台都打扫干净
Make sure the floors and countertops are clean before you lock up.
等等 你要我来打扫?
Wait. You want me to stay and clean?
你有意见?
Is that a problem?
- 没有 - 好孩子 明天见
-No. -Good boy. See you tomorrow.
(SIGHING )
到了
We're here.
(GASPING )
好好看看 Remy
Take a good long look, Remy.
这就是那些觉得人类很好的老鼠
Now, this is what happens
他们接近人类的下场
when a rat gets a little too comfortable around humans.
敌人主宰着我们所在的世界
The world we live in belongs to the enemy.
我们必须小心翼翼的过活
We must live carefully.
物以类聚 人以群分 Remy
We look out for our own kind, Remy.
上天注定 我们就是我们
When all is said and done, we're all we've got.
- 不 - 什么?
-No. -What?
不 爸 我不相信 你是在告诉我 我的未来
No. Dad, I don't believe it. You're telling me that the future is...
只能落得如此下场?
Can only be more of this?
这就是事实 你改变不了自然
This is the way things are. You can't change nature.
改变就是自然的定律 爸 我们可以影响点什么的
Change is nature, Dad. The part that we can influence.
当我们决定后 就能改变
And it starts when we decide.
- 你去哪 - 和好运一起  向前走
-Where you going? -With luck, forward.
嘿
Hey! Yeah.
(SNORING )
(VEHICLE ARRIVING )
(MOANING )
(LINGUINI MOANS )
别这样
(SLEEPILY) Stop it.
(RATTLING OUTSIDE)
(DEEP BREATH)
早
Good morning.
(CLEARING THROAT)
早
Good morning.
我们的主厨请你喝酒了?
So, the chef, he invited you in for a drink?
了不起啊
That's big.
了不起 他说了些什么?
That's big. What did he say?
怎么?
What?
你不能告诉我?
What, you can't tell me?
Oh!
原谅我打探你和主厨密切的私人关系
Forgive me for intruding on your deep, personal relationship with the chef.
我知道怎么回事了
Oh, I see how it is.
你把我教你的那些厨房诀窍告诉主厨
You get me to teach you a few kitchen tricks
然后一脚把我蹬开?
to dazzle the boss and then you blow past me?
醒醒 醒醒
Wake up. Wake up.
我以为你是与众不同的
I thought you were different.
我以为你觉得我也是与众不同的
I thought you thought I was different.
我以为
I thought...
(SNORING )
我没必要帮你
I didn't have to help you!
如果我只为自己好 我就让你去沦落了
If I looked out only for myself, I would have let you drown!
但是
But...
我想让你成功 我喜欢你
I wanted you to succeed. I liked you.
我的错
My mistake.
Colette 等等 等等 Colette
Colette. Wait, wait. Colette!
完了 小厨师 我做不下去了
It's over, Little Chef. I can't do it anymore.
Colette 等等 等等 别骑摩托走
Colette! Wait, wait! Don't motorcycle away.
听着 我不太会说话 也不太会做菜
Look, I'm no good with words. I'm no good with food either.
要不是你的帮助
At least not without your help.
我恨过于谦虚 这是说谎的另一种方式
I hate false modesty. It's just another way to lie.
- 你有天赋 - 没有 真的 不是我
-(SIGHS ) You have talent. -No, but I don't! Really! It's not me.
当没照着你给的食谱做菜
When I added that extra ingredient
添加其他材料的时候
instead of following the recipe like you said,
那也不是我
(CHUCKLING ) that wasn't me either.
- 你什么意思 - 我的意思我不该那么做
-What do you mean? -I mean, I wouldn't have done that.
我应该按照食谱
I would've followed the recipe.
我应该照着你的建议
I would've followed your advice.
我应该照着你的建议直到世界终结
I would've followed your advice to the ends of the earth.
- 因为我爱你...的建议 - 但是
-Because I love your advice. -But...
但是
But I...
别说
Don't do it.
我有个秘密 有点难以置信
I have a secret. It's sort of disturbing.
(TITTERING )
- 我有个老... - 什么 你什么
-I have a... -(STUTTERING ) What? You...
- 我有老... - 你老激动?
-I have a ra... -You have a rash?
不 不  不 我有这个... 一个小小的
No, no, no. I have this... This tiny little...
小小的
Little...
小小的大厨告诉我怎么做
(SPEAKING QUICKLY) A tiny chef who tells me what to do.
一个小厨师?
(IN DISBELIEF) A tiny chef?
是的 是的 他...
Yes. Yes. He's...
- 他在这里 - 在你的脑子里?
-He's up here. -In your brain?
(GRUNTING )
告诉你为什么就这么难? 好 这么来说
Why is it so hard to talk to you? Okay. Here we go.
你刺激了我 我准备不惜一切后果
You inspire me. I'm going to risk it all.
我冒着被你看作史上最蠢的白痴
I'm going to risk looking like the biggest idiot psycho you've ever seen.
你想知道为什么我学的这么快
You want to know why I'm such a fast learner?
你想知道为什么我是如此出色的厨师?
You want to know why I'm such a great cook?
别笑我 马上让你看
Don't laugh! I'm going to show you!
别 别
No! No!
(GRUNTING )
(TYPEWRITER CLICKING )
- 这是什么 Ambrister? - Gusteau的
-What is it, Ambrister? -Gusteau's.
- 终于关门了 是不是 - 没有
-Finally closing, is it? -No.
- 资金困难? - 不是 是...
-More financial trouble? -No, it's...
宣布了微波鸡蛋卷的新做法?
Announced a new line of microwave egg rolls?
是什么 是什么 快说
What? What? Spit it out.
卷土重来了 大受欢迎
(STUTTERING ) It's come back. It's popular.
- 我很久都没有评论Gusteau了 - 是的 先生
-I haven't reviewed Gusteau's in years. -No, sir.
最后一次是在旅行手册上
My last review condemned it
是的 先生
-to the tourist trade. -Yes, sir.
我说 Gusteau终于找到了 自己在历史上的位置
I said, "Gusteau has finally found his rightful place in history
与另一外著名的大厨并驾齐驱
"right alongside another equally famous chef,
Boyardee先生
(IN DISGUST) "Monsieur Boyardee."
感动
Touché.
这是我最后的留言 我最后的评论
That is where I left it. That was my last word.
- 最后的话 - 是的
-The last word. -Yes.
告诉我 Ambrister
Then tell me, Ambrister,
他怎么可能又受欢迎了
how could it be popular?
不 不 不 不 不 不
No, no, no, no, no, no, no!
DNA匹配 一切检测都说明
The DNA matches, the timing works, everything checks out.
他是Gusteau的儿子
He is Gusteau's son.
这不可能 这都是设计好了的
This can't just happen! The whole thing is a setup!
那个孩子知道
The boy knows!
看看他 装出一副傻瓜样
Look at him out there, pretending to be an idiot.
他把我的心当作小猫的什么球来耍
He's toying with my mind like a cat with a ball of... Something.
- 毛线球? - 对 耍我
-String? -Yes! Playing dumb.
- 用那老鼠来耍我 - 老鼠?
-Taunting me with that rat. -Rat?
他和那老鼠勾结着
Yes. He's consorting with it.
故意让我觉得那老鼠很重要
Deliberately trying to make me think it's important.
- 老鼠 - 正是
-The rat. -Exactly!
老鼠很重要?
Is the rat important?
当然不是 他故意让我们以为老鼠很重要
Of course not! He just wants me to think that it is.
我知道这是什么把戏了
Oh, I see the theatricality of it.
那天晚上我让他把老鼠干掉
A rat appears on the boy's first night, I order him to kill it.
现在他想要这老鼠阴魂不散
And now he wants me to see it everywhere.
(EX CITEDLY) Ooh!
在这里 不对 在这里
It's here! No, it isn't, it's here!
我看到什么了 我疯了吗? 到底有没有幽灵鼠
Am I seeing things, am I crazy? Is there a phantom rat or is there not?
但是 不不不
But, oh, no!
我才不会掉进他的圈套
I refuse to be sucked into his little game of...
我要不要也把这个考虑进去? 关于你的
Should I be concerned about this? About you?
(SIGHING )
Huh?
我不能解雇他 他现在是万众瞩目
I can't fire him. He's getting attention.
我要是辞退他 人人都会问为什么
If I fire him now, everyone will wonder why.
这是我最不想人们探究的问题
And the last thing I want is people looking into this.
你到底在担心什么?
What are you so worried about?
万众瞩目有什么不好
Isn't it good to have the press?
Gusteau的大名上新闻有什么不好?
Isn't it good to have Gusteau's name getting headlines?
但登的是他的照片
Not if they're over his face!
Gusteau已经有了形象代言人 多么憨厚 可爱 亲切
Gusteau's already has a face, and it's fat and lovable and familiar.
而且卖的奇好 大把大把的银子
And it sells burritos! Millions and millions of burritos!
三天之后就是最后期限
The deadline passes in three days.
不管他有没有价值你都可以解雇他
Then you can fire him whenever he ceases to be valuable
没人会知道的
and no one will ever know.
我担心的 倒是你给我的他头发的样本
I was worried about the hair sample you gave me.
- 我得重新把样本送回实验室 - 为什么
-I had to send them back to the lab. -Why?
因为第一次的检测结果是齿类动物
Because the first time it came back identified as rodent hair.
- 不 不 不 - 什么?
-No, no, no. -LINGUINl: What?
试试这个 这个更好
Try this. It's better.
(GRUNTING )
(SIGHING )
因为你...
Well, because you...
Whoa!
(BOTH LAUGHING )
(LINGUINI LAUGHING )
(GASPING )
(PEOPLE CHATTERING )
老鼠
Rat!
(PEOPLE SCREAMING )
恶心的小东西
WOMAN: Disgusting little creatures.
忽然我意识到 自己有多么脆弱
REMY: I was reminded how fragile it all was.
意识到这个世界是怎么看待我的
How the world really saw me.
而且就这么不断变好
And it just kept getting better.
Remy
EMILE: Remy!
呲! 呲!
Psst! Psst!
嘿 小弟
Hey, hey, hey, little brother!
我们还担心你不会出来呢
We were afraid you weren't going to, you know, show up.
- 嘿 Remy 你怎么样 - 你告诉他们了?
-Hey, Remy! How you doing? -You told them?
Emile 我告诉过你不许和别人说的
Emile, that's exactly what I said not to do!
你了解他们啊 他们都是我的朋友
But you know these guys. They're my friends.
我以为你说的不是他们
I didn't think you meant them.
听着 我很抱歉
(GROANING ) Look, I'm sorry.
别和我道歉 和他们去道歉
Don't tell me you're sorry, tell them you're sorry.
- 有什么问题吗? - 没有
-Is there a problem over here? -No, there is not.
等着
Wait here.
锁上了?
It's locked?
Hmm...
Remy 你在这里干什么
Remy, what are you doing in here?
Emile来了 还带着...
Okay. Emile shows up with...
我告诉过他不准来 他是大嘴巴
Okay, I said not to. I told him... He goes and blabs to...
悲剧啊
Yeah, it's a disaster.
不管了 他们饿了 食品柜锁了 我需要钥匙
Anyway, they're hungry, the food safe is locked and I need the key.
- 他们要你去偷吃的? - 是 不是 这个
-They want you to steal food? -Yes. No! It's...
情况很复杂 他们是家人 他们不像你那么有理想
It's complicated. It's family. They don't have your ideals.
理想? 如果Fancy Pants有什么理想
(IN SOUTHERN ACCENT) Ideals? If Chef Fancy Pants had any ideals,
你是不是还要搞个烤肉派对?
you think I'd be hawking barbecue over here?
或者墨西哥卷?
(IN MEXICAN ACCENT) Or microwave burritos?
或者 口...我说 口水鸡?
Or, Tooth, I say, Tooth Pick'n Chicken?
和玉米狗一样法国风味!
About as French as a corn dog!
马上就来
(BARKING ) Coming soon!
我们在开创新的销售方案
We're inventing new ways to sell out over here.
你又欠咬了吧
(IN SCOTTISH ACCENT) Will ye be wanting some haggis bites?
他们用的是我的创意 Remy
I cannot control how they use my image, Remy.
- 我死了 - 闭嘴
-I am dead! -Can you guys shut up?
我得思考 你们都疯了 我要是不能让他们闭嘴
I've got to think! Word's getting out. If I can't keep them quiet,
整个家族都会跟在我屁股后面要吃的
the entire clan's gonna be after me with their mouths open and...
在这里
Here it is.
嘿 你的遗嘱
Hey. Your will!
- 这个有意思 介意我... - 不介意
-Oh, this is interesting. Mind if I... -Not at all.
Linguini?
为什么Linguini在你的遗嘱里
Why would Linguini be filed with your will?
这以前是我的办公室
This used to be my office.
他是你的儿子?
He's your son?
- 我有个儿子 - 你怎么会不知道
-I have a son? -How could you not know this?
我只是你脑袋里的想象人物 你都不知道 我怎么可能知道
I am a figment of your imagination. You did not know, how could I?
你的儿子才是这家餐厅的合法继承人
Well, your son is the rightful owner of this restaurant!
(GASPING )
啊 老鼠
No! No! The rat!
(GROANING )
(SCREAMING )
- 抱歉 主厨 - 那只老鼠 偷了我的我文件
-Sorry, chef. -The rat! It's stolen my documents!
- 它逃跑了! - 嘿 主厨先生!
-It's getting away! -LALO: Hey, Mr. Chef!
(HORN BLARING )
(SCREAMING )
(GRUNTS )
(GROANS )
(LAUGHING )
你!
(GASPS ) You!
- 滚出我的办公室 - 不是他在你办公室 是你在他的办公室
-Get out of my office. -He's not in your office. You are in his.
干杯 Linguini!
Bottoms up, Linguini!
(LE FES TIN PLAYING )
干杯 耶!
HORST: Cheers, ja.
(ALL CHUCKLING )
(GRUMBLING )
(HORST EX CLAIMING ANGRILY)
主厨! 主厨! 主厨Linguini!
REPORTER 1 : Chef! Chef! REPORTER 2: Chef Linguini!
(REPORTERS CLAMORING )
你快速成名 但未经过正规的训练
Your rise has been meteoric, yet you have no formal training.
你的天分后有什么秘密?
What is the secret to your genius?
秘密? 你想知道真相吗?
LINGUINl: Secret? You want the truth?
我是Gusteau的儿子 我猜这是遗传
(HESITANTLY) I am Gusteau's son. It's in my blood I guess.
但你也是最近才知道真相啊
FEMALE REPORTER: But you weren't aware of that fact until very recently.
是的
No.
它直接导致了你接管这家餐馆
MALE REPORTER: And it resulted in your taking ownership of this restaurant.
你是怎么发现的?
How did you find out?
呃 我就是知道了
Well, some part of me just knew.
关于Gusteau的事吗?
The Gusteau part?
- 你的灵感从何而来? - 灵感来源有很多种
-Where do you get your inspiration? -Inspiration has many names.
- 我的灵感来自于Colette - 什么?
-Mine is named Colette. -What?
(REMY SQUEAKING )
牙缝塞住了
Something's stuck in my teeth.
(RINGING )
卫生检察员
Health Inspector.
我要报告一起鼠患事件
I wish to report a rat infestation.
发生在我的...
It's taken over my...
Gusteau餐馆
(STAMMERING ) Gusteau's restaurant.
Gusteau餐馆 是吗?
Gusteau's, eh?
我可以去拜访一下 让我瞧瞧 三个月前就查过了
I can drop by. Let's see. First opening is three months.
必须马上去! 那是家美食餐馆!
It must happen now! It's a gourmet restaurant!
先生 我知道了 如有人取消安排 我会先去拜访这家餐馆
Monsieur, I have the information. If someone cancels, I'll slot you in.
但是老鼠! 你一定...
(STAMMERING ) But the rat! You must...
(DIAL TONE DRONING )
它偷走了我的文件
It stole my documents.
营业时间已经到了
It's past opening time.
他本该一小时前就结束采访
(GROANING ) He should have finished an hour ago.
(LAUGHING )
你好 亲爱的 和我们一起聊吧
Bonjour, ma chérie. Join us.
我们还在讨论我的灵感来源呢
We were just talking about my inspiration.
是的 他把它叫做他的小厨师
Yes, he calls it his tiny chef.
(SQUEAKING )
不是那个 亲爱的 我是说你
Not that, dearest. I meant you.
(DOOR OPENING )
(REPORTERS GASPING )
- 是他 - Ego?
-It's him. -Ego?
Anton Ego!
就是那个Ego吗?
REPORTER: Is that Ego?
我无法相信
I can't believe it.
- 你是Linguini先生? - 你好
-You are Monsieur Linguini? -Hello.
原谅我打断了你的提前庆祝
Pardon me for interrupting your premature celebration,
既然你是游戏的新选手
but I thought it only fair to give you a sporting chance
我想 给你次机会很公平
as you are new to this game.
- 游戏? - 没错
-Game? -Yes.
你一直在没有对手的情况下比赛
And you've been playing without an opponent.
也许你已经猜到了 这不合规矩
Which is, as you may have guessed, against the rules.
你是Anton Ego
You're Anton Ego.
(CHUCKLING )
对在快车道的人来说 你开得太慢了
You're slow for someone in the fast lane.
(PEOPLE GASPING )
对喜欢美食的人来说 你太瘦了
And you're thin for someone who likes food.
(ALL GASPING IN SHOCK)
我不是"喜欢"美食 我热爱它
I don't like food. I love it.
如果我不热爱 我就不会吃
If I don't love it, I don't swallow.
(GULPING )
明晚 我会带着极高的期待回来
I will return tomorrow night with high expectations.
希望你不会让我失望
Pray you don't disappoint me.
(REPORTERS MURMURING )
听着 我们不想粗鲁 但我们是法国人 现在是晚餐时间
Listen, we hate to be rude, but we're French, and it's dinnertime.
她意思是说 "现在是晚餐时间 我们是法国人"
She meant to say, "It's dinnertime and we're French."
别对我摆出那副表情
Don't give me that look.
你在记者面前让我分心
You were distracting me in front of the press.
你一直在拉我的头发 我如何能专心呢?
How am I supposed to concentrate with you yanking on my hair all the time?
还有一件事
And that's another thing.
你的建议并不是这里唯一重要的
Your opinion isn't the only one that matters here.
Colette也知道如何烹饪
Colette knows how to cook, too, you know.
好吧 就是这样!
All right, that's it!
你歇歇吧 小厨师
You take a break, Little Chef.
我不是你的小狗狗
I'm not your puppet,
你也不是狗狗的主人!
and you're not my puppet-controlling guy!
那只老鼠才是主厨
(GASPS ) The rat is the cook.
你冷静一下 想想清楚 小厨师
You cool off and get your mind right, Little Chef.
Ego就要来了 我需要集中精力!
Ego is coming, and I need to focus!
(GRUNTING )
你这愚蠢的...
You stupid...
(GRUMBLING ANGRILY)
哇 我从未见过他这样
Wow. I have never seen that before.
对 就象你是他的绒毛小兔什么的
Yeah, it's like you're his fluffy bunny or something.
(RATS LAUGHING )
我很抱歉 Remy
EMILE: I'm sorry, Remy.
我知道老鼠太多了
I know there are too many guys.
- 我试着把数量限制在... - 你知道不?
-I tried to limit... -You know what?
没事的 我以前太自私了
It's okay. I've been selfish.
- 你们饿了吗? - 你开玩笑吗?
-You guys hungry? -Are you kidding?
好吧 晚餐我请客 我们在关门后进去
All right. Dinner's on me. We'll go after closing time.
- 事实上... - 怎么
-In fact... -Yeah.
告诉爸爸 把全家族都带来
...tell Dad to bring the whole clan.
小厨师?
Little Chef?
真棒 儿子 间谍工作 我清楚它有多大的吸引力
This is great, Son. An inside job. I see the appeal.
(SHUSHING )
(CLICKS TONGUE)
Oof!
(BECKONS )
(KE YS JINGLING )
(ALL GASP)
小厨师?
Little Chef?
Hey, Little Chef.
我还以为你回公寓了
I thought you went back to the apartment.
发现你不在那里时 我不知道...
Then when you weren't there, I don't know...
我们就那样把事情一撂 似乎不太对 所以...
It didn't seem right to leave things the way that we did, so...
听着 我不想吵架
Look, I don't want to fight.
我一直处在很大的...压力下
I've been under a lot of, you know, pressure.
这么短时间内 很多事都变了 你知道吗?
A lot has changed in not very much time, you know?
我突然成了一个Gusteau的儿子
I'm suddenly a Gusteau.
而我必须表现得象个Gusteau 否则 你知道的
And I got to be a Gusteau or, you know,
大家会对我失望的
people will be disappointed.
这很古怪
It's weird.
我以前从未让任何人失望过
You know, I've never disappointed anyone before,
因为没有谁对我有过期待
because nobody's ever expected anything of me.
现在他们期待我的唯一原因...
And the only reason anyone expects anything from me now
就在于你
is because of you.
我对你不太公平
I haven't been fair to you.
你从没让我失望 我该永远牢记这点
You've never failed me, and I should never forget that.
你一直是我的好朋友
You've been a good friend.
任何人希望得到的最可敬的朋友...
The most honorable friend a guy could ever ask...
(GROANS )
这是什么?
What is this?
发生什么事了?
What's going on?
什么...
What...
嘿...
Hey...
你在...
(STUTTERING ) You're...
你在偷食物? 你怎么可以?
You're stealing food? How could you?
你以为你是我朋友! 我信任过你!
I thought you were my friend! I trusted you!
滚出去! 你和你的老鼠朋友!
Get out! You and all your rat buddies!
再也不要回来
And don't come back
否则我会象餐馆处理害虫那样对你们!
or I'll treat you the way restaurants are supposed to treat pests!
你是对的 爸爸 我骗谁呢?
You're right, Dad. Who am I kidding?
我们就是我们 我们是老鼠
We are what we are, and we're rats.
他很快就走 现在你们知道如何进去了
Well, he'll leave soon, and now you know how to get in.
随便偷吧
Steal all you want.
- 你不来吗? - 我没胃口了
-You're not coming? -I've lost my appetite.
你今晚想要点什么 先生?
Do you know what you would like this evening, sir?
我想要把你的心串起来烤着吃 嘿嘿
Yes, I'd like your heart roasted on a spit.
(ANTON SNICKERING )
( AN TON SNICKERIN G)
(EX CLAIMS )
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
进来!
Come in!
今天是个大日子 你该对他们说点什么
Today's the big day. You should say something to them.
- 说什么呢? - 你是老板 激励一下他们
-Like what? -You are the boss. Inspire them.
注意
(MEEKLY) Attention.
大家请注意
(MORE CONFIDENTLY) Attention, everyone.
今晚非常重要
Tonight is a big night.
美食家即将光临 他极其自负 (Ego在英文里有自负的意思)
Appetite is coming, and he's going to have a big ego.
我是说 Ego先生 他就要来了 评论家
I mean, Ego. He's coming. The critic.
他会来点某道菜
And he's going to order something.
从我们菜单上点
Something from our menu.
我们得照着烹饪 除非他点冷门菜
And we'll have to cook it, unless he orders something cold.
你就是放不下心 对吗?
EMILE: Just can't leave it alone, can you?
你真不该在营业时间来这里 太不安全了
You really shouldn't be here during restaurant hours. It's not safe.
我饿死了!
I'm hungry!
我不是非吃餐馆里的食物才高兴
And I don't need the inside food to be happy.
关键是 我的朋友 不要挑食
The key, my friend, is to not be picky.
- 帮我望风 - 不 等等!
-Observe. -No, wait!
- 哦 不! 不 不! 我们怎么办? - 我去叫爸爸来
-Oh, no! No, no! What do we do? -(STUTTERING ) I'll go get Dad.
(SNICKERING )
也许你觉得你是主厨 但你仍然是只老鼠
You might think you are a chef but you are still only a rat.
当然了 他上次来这里后 把餐馆降低了一个等级
Sure he took away a star last time he reviewed this place.
当然了 这很可能杀死了...爸爸
Sure it probably killed... Dad.
- 这真是糟糕透顶的鼓励辞 - 但我要告诉你们一件事...
-This is very bad juju right here. -But I'll tell you one thing...
- Ego来了 - Ego? 他已经来了?
-Ego is here. -Ego? He is here?
Anton Ego只是个普通顾客 我们干吧!
Anton Ego is just another customer. Let's cook!
耶! 我们开始...
Yeah! Let's...
好吧
Okay.
我有个简单的交易
So I have in mind a simple arrangement.
你为我创造出一系列全新的 主厨Skinner的冷冻美食
You will create for me a new line of Chef Skinner frozen foods.
作为回报 我就放你条生路
And I, in return, will not kill you.
(SNICKERING )
再见 老鼠!
Au revoir, rat!
(SIGHS )
决定今晚想点什么菜吗 先生?
Do you know what you would like this evening, sir?
是的 我想是的
Yes, I think I do.
看过许多对你们新厨师的过热吹捧后
After reading a lot of overheated puffery about your new cook,
你知道我渴望什么吗?
you know what I'm craving?
一点点的创新
A little perspective.
就那样 我想要某种新鲜的 纯净的 富有创意的菜式
That's it. I'd like some fresh, clear, well seasoned perspective.
至于配哪种上等葡萄酒 你有好建议吗?
Can you suggest a good wine to go with that?
- 搭配什么 先生? - 创意菜啊 最独特的菜 我想是这样?
-With what, sir? -Perspective. Fresh out, I take it?
我是...
I am...
很好 既然你们没什么创意
Very well. Since you're all out of perspective
似乎这该死的城里也没其他人能做
and no one else seems to have it in this bloody town,
我提个交易
I'll make you a deal.
你提供美食 我提供创意
You provide the food, I'll provide the perspective.
它得和1947年产的Cheval Blanc红酒 相得益彰
Which would go nicely with a bottle of Cheval Blanc 1 94 7.
我恐怕...
I'm afraid I...
你的晚餐选择?
Your dinner selection?
告诉你们主厨Linguini 随便他为我做什么菜都行
Tell your Chef Linguini that I want whatever he dares to serve me.
告诉他 用他最拿手的菜式说服我
Tell him to hit me with his best shot.
那位先生点什么 我就点什么
I will have whatever he is having.
- 那么说 我们已经放弃了 - 你干嘛这样说?
-So, we have given up. -Why do you say that?
我们在轿车后备箱的笼子里
We are in a cage inside the car trunk
在冷冻食品中寄托未来
awaiting a future in frozen food products.
不 我才是在笼子里的那个 是我放弃了
No, I'm the one in a cage. I've given up.
你是自由的
You are free.
你想像我自由 我才是自由的
I am only as free as you imagine me to be.
象你一样
As you are.
哦 得了 我讨厌伪装 为我父亲 我伪装成老鼠
Oh, please. I'm sick of pretending. I pretend to be a rat for my father.
通过Linguini 我伪装成人类
I pretend to be a human through Linguini.
我假装你存在 所以我有人聊天!
I pretend you exist so I have someone to talk to!
你只能告诉我 我早就知道的事!
You only tell me stuff I already know!
我知道我是谁! 干嘛要你来告诉我?
I know who I am! Why do I need you to tell me?
我干嘛需要伪装自己?
Why do I need to pretend?
(CHUCKLING )
可你不需要伪装 Remy
But you don't, Remy.
你从不需要
You never did.
(CRASHING )
不 还有我那一半!
No. My other left!
爸爸? 爸爸 我在这里!
REMY: (MUFFLED) Dad? Dad, I'm in here!
我在后备箱里 到底怎么...
I'm inside the trunk! What the...
爸爸!
Dad!
- 嘿 小弟弟! - Emile!
-Hey, little brother! -Emile!
我爱死你们了!
I love you guys!
你去哪?
Where are you going?
回餐馆去 没有我 他们一定完蛋了
Back to the restaurant. They'll fail without me.
- 你干嘛还要关心他们? - 因为我是名厨师!
-Why do you care? -Because I'm a cook!
(STAFF CLAMORING )
那是你的食谱
It's your recipe.
你怎会记不得自己的食谱?
How can you not know your own recipe?
我没写下来 就是灵机一动想出来的
I didn't write it down. It just came to me.
那就再发挥一下灵机吧? 我们做不了这个!
Then make it come to you again, ja? Because we can't serve this!
我的菜单做好了没?
Where's my order?
我们就不能做点别的什么? 做不是我发明的菜式?
Can't we serve something else? Something I didn't invent?
他们点的就是这个
This is what they're ordering.
让他们点其他菜 告诉他们 这个菜卖完了
Make them order something else. Tell them we're all out.
不能说卖完了 我们才刚开门营业
We cannot be all out. We just opened.
我有个主意 干嘛不照他们点的做!
I have another idea. What if we serve them what they order!
我们会撑过去的 只要告诉我们你怎么做的
We will make it. Just tell us what you did.
我不知道我怎么做的
I don't know what I did.
我们得和顾客解释一下
We need to tell the customers something.
告诉他们...告诉他们..
Then tell them... Tell them...
(SCREAMING )
哈?
Huh?
- 别去 - Remy Remy
-Don't do it. -Remy. Remy.
别去! 快停下! 他们会看见你的 停下!
EMILE: Don't! Stop! They'll see you. Stop.
我们不是在说我 我们是在说怎样做正确的...
We're not talking about me. We're talking about what to do right...
老鼠!
Rats!
- Remy! - 快拿刀
-Remy! -Get my knife.
别碰他!
Don't touch him!
谢谢回来 小主厨
(WHISPERING ) Thanks for coming back, Little Chef.
我知道这事听起来很荒唐 但...
I know this sounds insane, but...
有时真相就这么荒唐
Well, the truth sounds insane sometimes.
但那并不代表 那就不是...
But that doesn't mean it's not
真相了
(STAMMERING ) the truth.
真相就是 我毫无烹饪天分
And the truth is, I have no talent at all.
但这只老鼠 他才是制作所有美食的那位
But this rat, he's the one behind these recipes.
他才是厨师 真正的大厨 他一直躲在我的帽子里
He's the cook. The real cook. He's been hiding under my toque.
他一直指导我的行动
He's been controlling my actions.
(ALL GASPING )
由于他 我才能做出让大家激动的菜式
He's the reason I can cook the food that's exciting everyone.
因为他 Ego才会坐在那扇门外
The reason Ego is outside that door.
因为他的天赋 你们才信任我
You've been giving me credit for his gift.
我知道这很难让人相信
I know it's a hard thing to believe.
但是 嘿 你们相信我能烹饪 对吗?
But, hey, you believed I could cook, right?
(CHUCKLES )
听着 这方法管用 虽然很蠢 但它管用
Look, this works. It's crazy, but it works.
我们能成为全巴黎最好的餐馆
We can be the greatest restaurant in Paris,
这只老鼠 这只才华横溢的小厨师 能把我们带到那个高度
and this rat, this brilliant Little Chef, can lead us there.
你们怎么说? 和我一起干吗?
What do you say? You with me?
(SIGHS )
(MOTORC YCLE STARTING )
(GROANS )
(HORN BLARING )
(TIRES SKIDDING )
(HORNS HONKING )
(SIGHS )
爸爸
Dad.
爸爸 我不知道该说些什么
Dad, I don't know what to say.
我看错了你朋友 也看错了你
I was wrong about your friend and about you.
我不想你觉得我 热爱这里更甚于家庭
I don't want you to think I'm choosing this over family.
我没法在我的两种生活间做出选择
I can't choose between two halves of myself.
我不是在说烹饪 我说的是胆量
I'm not talking about cooking. I'm talking about guts.
这事对你来说真有那么重要?
This really means that much to you?
(WHISTLES )
(ALL CHATTERING )
我们不是厨师 但我们是一家人
We're not cooks, but we are family.
你告诉我们该怎么做 我们来完成任务
You tell us what to do, and we'll get it done.
- 快阻止那个卫生检查员! - 三角洲特种分队 出发 出发 出发!
-Stop that health inspector! -Delta Team, go, go, go, go!
剩下的留在这里 帮助Remy
The rest of you stay and help Remy.
(ELECTRIC ENGINE WHIRRING )
(ENGINE STARTS )
第3组 处理鱼类 第4组 负责烘烤
Team three will be handling fish. Team four, roasted items.
第5组 烤肉  第6组 负责调料 各就各位 行动 行动!
Team five, grill. Team six, sauces. Get to your stations. Let's go, go, go!
负责食品的老鼠只能用两条后腿走路
Those handling food will walk on two legs.
我们需要人手招呼顾客
We need someone to wait tables.
很抱歉上菜慢了 但今晚我们缺人手
I'm sorry for any delay, but we're a little short tonight.
没关系 慢慢来
Please, take all of the time you need.
他又一次迟到了 怎么突然他...
He came in late one more time and all of a sudden he...
确保牛排要美味鲜嫩
REMY: Make sure that steak is nice and tenderized.
动起来 戳一下再做  戳一下再做
Work it. Yeah. Stick and move. Stick and move.
小心法式黄油炸鱼 少放盐 多放黄油
Easy with that sole meunière. Less salt. More butter.
只能用麦墨雷特奶酪
Only use the mimolette cheese.
哇! 象绘画那样调制撒拉
Whoa! Compose the salad like you were painting a picture.
撒拉里的香料别放多了
Not too much vinaigrette on that salade composée.
别让奶油结成块 继续搅拌
Don't let that beurre blanc separate. Keep whisking.
小心煮扇贝 先尝尝味道 所有调羹往下
Gently poach the scallops. Taste check. Spoons down.
好的 盐太多了 很好
Good. Too much salt. Good.
别让汤煮沸 那会使野鸡肉变硬 Emile!
Don't boil the consommé, it'll toughen the pheasant. Emile!
抱歉
Sorry.
Colette 等等! Colette
Colette, wait! Colette.
- 你回来了 Colette... - 啥都别说了
-You came back. Colette... -Don't say a word.
如果我再多想 也许会改主意
If I think about it, I might change my mind.
只要告诉我 老鼠打算做什么菜就好
Just tell me what the rat wants to cook.
普罗旺斯焖菜? 它是乡下菜
Ratatouille? It's a peasant dish.
你确定要用这道菜招待Ego吗?
Are you sure you want to serve this to Ego?
(DISHWARE SHATTERING )
(MUFFLED EX CLAIMING )
怎么了? 我在做普罗旺斯焖菜
What? I am making ratatouille.
(SCOFFS )
那你是如何烹制它的?
Well, how would you prepare it?
普罗旺斯焖菜? 他们一定在开玩笑
Ratatouille? They must be joking.
(WHIMPERS )
(SNIFFLING )
(THUDDIN G)
Mmm.
不 不可能
No, it can't be.
谁做的普罗旺斯焖菜? 我一定要知道!
Who cooked the ratatouille? I demand to know!
(GASPING )
(CLATTERING )
(MUFFLED GROANING )
我都不记得最近一次...
I can't remember the last time
要求侍者转达我对主厨的赞美 是什么时候了
I asked a waiter to give my compliments to the chef.
眼下我正处在一个奇特的位置
And now I find myself in the extraordinary position
我的侍者就是我的主厨
of having my waiter be the chef.
谢谢 但今晚我只是你的侍者
Thanks, but I'm just your waiter tonight.
那么我该感谢谁呢?
Then who do I thank for the meal?
稍等片刻
Excuse me a minute.
(MUFFLED ARGUING )
你一定就是主厨了...
You must be the chef...
如果你想见主厨 你得等到...
If you wish to meet the chef, you will have to wait
所有顾客都离开为止
until all the other customer have gone.
那就这样吧
So be it.
一开始 Ego认为那是个玩笑
REMY: At first, Ego thinks it's a joke.
但随着Linguini的解释 Ego的微笑消失了
But as Linguini explains, Ego's smile disappears.
(RATS SQUEAKING )
除了偶尔提个问题 他面无表情
He doesn't react beyond asking an occasional question.
故事说完后 Ego站了起来 感谢我们的晚餐
And when the story is done, Ego stands, thanks us for the meal...
谢谢你们的晚餐
Thank you for the meal.
然后就离开了 再没说别的
...and leaves without another word.
第二天 他的评论发表了
The following day his review appears.
在许多方面 评论家的工作很轻松
E GO: In many ways, the work of a critic is easy.
我们不怎么需要冒险 却能享受...
We risk very little, yet enjoy a position over those
比那些提供自身作品供我们评判的人 高出一等的地位
who offer up their work and their selves to our judgment.
我们热衷于批评别人 写者和读者都觉得有趣
We thrive on negative criticism, which is fun to write and to read.
但我们批评家必须面对的苦涩事实是: 总的说来
But the bitter truth we critics must face is that in the grand scheme of things,
任何普通的垃圾食品都可能比...
the average piece of junk is probably more meaningful
我们对它的批评 来得更有意义
than our criticism designating it so.
但有时 评论家真正需要冒险的是
But there are times when a critic truly risks something
发现和呵护新生事物
and that is in the discovery and defense of the new.
这世界对新天才 新创意常常太过刻薄
The world is often unkind to new talent, new creations.
这些后起之秀需要朋友
The new needs friends.
昨晚 我品尝了某道全新的
Last night, I experienced something new,
由一位奇特而又出乎意料的厨师 制作的美味佳肴
an extraordinary meal from a singularly unexpected source.
那道美味和它的制作者...
To say that both the meal and its maker
同时挑战了我对美食的偏见
have challenged my preconceptions about fine cooking
我的看法太保守了
is a gross understatement.
他们彻底颠覆了我的观点
They have rocked me to my core.
过去 我毫不隐晦地蔑视...
In the past, I have made no secret of my disdain
Gusteau主厨的名言"人人能烹饪"
for Chef Gusteau's famous motto, "Anyone can cook. "
但直到现在 我才真正理解他的意思
But I realize only now do I truly understand what he meant.
不是每个人都能成为伟大的艺术家
Not everyone can become a great artist,
但伟大的艺术家可能来自任何地方
but a great artist can come from anywhere.
很难想像还有比Gusteau餐馆的...
It is difficult to imagine more humble origins
天才厨师出身更为低贱的
than those of the genius now cooking at Gusteau's,
这位厨师 在我这个评论家看来
who is, in this critic's opinion,
是全法国最顶尖的大厨
nothing less than the finest chef in France.
我很快将再次光临Gusteau餐馆 期待更多美味佳肴
I will be returning to Gusteau's soon, hungry for more.
那是个美好的夜晚
REMY: It was a great night.
我生命中最快乐的一天
( CHUCKLIN G) The happiest of my life.
但生活中唯一可预言的就是 它的不可预言性
But the only thing predictable about life is its unpredictability.
我们不得不放了Skinner和卫生检查员
Well, we had to let Skinner and the health inspector loose,
当然了 他们告发了我们
and of course they ratted us out.
食物不再重要
The food didn't matter.
一旦传出厨房里有老鼠的谣言
Once it got out there were rats in the kitchen,
伙计 餐馆被迫关闭
oh, man, the restaurant was closed
Ego失去了工作和他的名声
and Ego lost his job and his credibility.
但别为他感到难过
But don't feel too bad for him.
作为一个小生意投资者 他干得不错
He's doing very well as a small business investor.
- 他似乎很快乐 - 你怎么知道?
-He seems very happy. -How do you know?
(LE FES TIN PLAYING )
我该走了 晚餐高峰时间到了
Got to go. Dinner rush.
你知道他有多喜欢这道菜
You know how he likes it.
谢谢 小厨师
Thanks, Little Chef.
今晚你需要上甜点吗?
Can I interest you in a dessert this evening?
- 难道你不总是这样做吗? - 你喜欢什么甜点?
-Don't you always? -Which one would you like?
给我上份惊喜
Surprise me.
今晚你需要上甜点吗?
Can I interest you in a dessert this evening?
(RATS CHUCKLING )
相信我 这故事我说起来更生动 好吧?
Hey, believe me, that story gets better when I tell it, okay?
快来 送点吃的过来 我们饿死了!
Come on. Bring some food over here, we're starving!